<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dissertatio de pace, &amp;c. Or, A discourse touching the peace &amp; concord of the Church. Wherein is elegantly and acutely argued, that not so much a bad opinion, as a bad life, excludes a Christian out of the kingdom of heaven; and that the things necessary to be known for the attainment of salvation, are very few and easie: and finally, that those, who pass amongst us under the name of hereticks, are notwithstanding to be tolerated.</title>
            <title>Dissertatio de pace. English</title>
            <author>Przypkowski, Samuel, 1592-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91322</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4133</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1495_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203302</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863291</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863291</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115483</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91322)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115483)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 191:E1495[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Dissertatio de pace, &amp;c. Or, A discourse touching the peace &amp; concord of the Church. Wherein is elegantly and acutely argued, that not so much a bad opinion, as a bad life, excludes a Christian out of the kingdom of heaven; and that the things necessary to be known for the attainment of salvation, are very few and easie: and finally, that those, who pass amongst us under the name of hereticks, are notwithstanding to be tolerated.</title>
                  <title>Dissertatio de pace. English</title>
                  <author>Przypkowski, Samuel, 1592-1670.</author>
                  <author>Biddle, John, 1615-1662,</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 64, [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ja: Cottrel, for Rich. Moone, at the seven stars in Paul's Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Przypkowski, Samuel.  Dissertatio de pace.</note>
                  <note>Translation sometimes attributed to John Biddle.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>With a final advertisement leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb. 7.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Socinianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religious tolerance --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Heretics, Christian --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church --  Unity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:115483:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:115483:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
DISSERTATIO <hi>de Pace,</hi> &amp;c. OR, A DISCOURSE Touching the PEACE &amp; CONCORD OF THE Church.</p>
            <p>Wherein is elegantly and acutely argued, That not ſo much a bad Opinion, as a bad Life, excludes a Chriſtian out of the kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; and that the things neceſſary to be known for the attainment of ſalvation, are very few and eaſie: and finally, that thoſe, who paſs amongſt us under the name of Hereticks, are notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to be tolerated.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Ja: Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>trel,</hi> for <hi>Rich. Moone,</hi> at the ſeven ſtars in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1653.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:115483:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115483:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:115483:3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115483:3"/>
            <head>The Publiſher TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Author of this Diſcourſe, Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Reader, a man, as it appeareth, both pious and learned, knowing that of all the Families and Societies of
<pb facs="tcp:115483:4"/>
Chriſtians, they are moſt hated, who by their Profeſſion and Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings maintain the Opinion of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinus</hi> touching the Eſſence and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chriſt, endeavoured by this Diſcourſe to abate the hatred of certain Zelots againſt the <hi>Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> not that he approved their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine (for he once and again diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owns it) but becauſe he was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that if the harſh judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of men were once mitiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted concerning the moſt odious Opinion of all, the heat of that bitter zeal wherewith Chriſtians are generally incited to perſecute diſſenters in Religion, would by degrees evaporate. But if thou, Chriſtian Reader, doſt from thy heart aſpire to the knowledge of GOD, and his Son Jeſus Chriſt, wherein, as Chriſt himſelf teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, eternal life doth conſiſt,
<pb facs="tcp:115483:4"/>
               <hi>Iohn</hi> 17. 3. fetch not the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereof either from <hi>Socinus,</hi> (a man otherwiſe of great under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in the myſtery of the Goſpel) nor from his Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, but being mindful of thoſe words, <hi>Luke</hi> 10. 22. <hi>None know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth who the Son is, but the Father; and who the Father is, but the Son, and he to whom the Son will reveal him;</hi> Lay aſide for a while Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſal Writings, together with thoſe prejudicate Opinions that have been inſtilled into thine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wary Underſtanding; and cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applying thy ſelf to the ſearch of the New Covenant, moſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently implore the Grace of Chriſt, that he would be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to manifeſt Himſelf and the Father to thee, and make no doubt but the true Light will at length illuminate the eyes of thy
<pb facs="tcp:115483:5"/>
minde, that thou mayſt walk in the way that leadeth unto Life. Farewel.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:115483:5"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <label>CHAP. I.</label>
               <item>THe lot of Truth and Innocencie in this world. A Gheſs of the Author touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf.</item>
               <label>CHAP. II.</label>
               <item>What things concerning God and Christ are neceſſary to be known unto ſalvation, and what are the parts of True Faith.</item>
               <label>CHAP. III.</label>
               <item>That ſincere Love towards God and Christ is ſufficient to Salvation; and that the ſame may be in ſuch as erre.</item>
               <label>CHAP. IIII.</label>
               <item>That though Faith and the Holy Spirit be the Gifts of God, yet erring perſons have and may have them.</item>
               <label>CHAP. V.</label>
               <item>That nothing but Diſobedience and Unbelief exclude a man from Eternal Salvation; and that ſuch as erre, are free from theſe. Whether bare Errors of the Underſtanding damn a man.</item>
               <label>CHAP. VI.</label>
               <item>That the things neceſſary to be known unto Salvation, are few and very ſimple, and eaſie to be underſtood by the ſimpleſt. Such is not the common doctrine touching the Trinity.</item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115483:6"/>
CHAP. VII.</label>
               <item>That there is not in this life a perfect know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, and of Divine Myſteries, but in the other life; and that Faith, Hope, and Charity, are ſufficient to Salvation.</item>
               <label>CHAP. VIII.</label>
               <item>A General Apologie for the <hi>Socinians,</hi> that they are not of ſuch a Perſwaſion out of Ambition, Avarice, Pleaſure, or Superſtition, nor offend out of any Malice, but onely out of the Care of their Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
               <label>CHAP. IX.</label>
               <item>An Anſwer to the Objection about reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the Conſent of the Church, for the Authority of the Scripture onely.</item>
               <label>CHAP. X.</label>
               <item>An Anſwer to three other Objections: a Compariſon of <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Doctrine touching Fatal Predeſtination, with the Doctrine of others.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XI.</label>
               <item>Reaſons and Examples for tolerating Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks; and who are true Hereticks.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XII.</label>
               <item>What Hereticks are to be excommunicated, what not; and a fuller Apologie for thoſe who in our Age paſs for Hereticks.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115483:6"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE Touching the PEACE &amp; CONCORD OF THE Church.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The lot of Truth and Innocencie in this world. A Gheſs of the Author touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>RUTH was never called into queſtion, but Innocencie was fain to plead for her ſelf at the ſame bar; nor hath the one been more hated, then the other always envied. Indeed, we men are very prone to evil, and therefore hate not onely the open freedom of a true judgement, but alſo the tacite cenſure of another's integrity. Nor is this a crime peculiar to our Age. 'Twas heretofore the diſpoſition of Wickedneſs, no leſs to fear the mute innocencie
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115483:7"/>
of another, then the living voice of a reprover; nor can it be otherwiſe hereafter, but that vertue ſhould become a goad to their ſenſes, whoſe mindes have been ſeized with vices. But though our wickedneſs may ſeem to have a kind of right to deteſt ſuch Truth, as toucheth the ulcers of ours ſins, yet why ſhould we abominate her that caſts a harmleſs eye towards heaven? Is it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, as both theſe cure the two diſeaſes of the minde, our Errors namely and our Vices, ſo we are delighted with both thoſe Diſtempers? Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly here lies the pinch. We are more enamoured of our Errours, then of all our dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, either becauſe they wink at the ſcapes and dalliance of our affections; or becauſe we are enraged againſt diſſenters with obſtinate preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice and frantick affectation of parties. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit we never erre with greater delight then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſenſe of divine matters, and are ſo far from acknowledging thoſe ſlips, (the witneſſes of humane imbecillity) that we account them for Oracles. Nor is our raſhneſs content to have pleaſed her ſelf herein, but obtrudeth her noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon others againſt their wills: and the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe of determining is wont to aſſume ſo much to it ſelf, that it excludeth a liberty of diſſenting in the ſmalleſt tittle. After the judgements of mankinde had been oppreſſed in this maner, the Church for many ages was overſpread with thick darkneſs, whilſt the greateſt part had neither liberty to utter what they underſtood, nor liſt to underſtand what they might not utter. And though there have been ſo many windes and ſtorms of Contention in the Chriſtian world, yet have they not to this very day been able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115483:7"/>
ſo great a fog, ſo that amidſt the clouds diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed over all the skie, there are ſome few who through the intervals behold the whole face of the ſun; whilſt others ſee afar off ſome gleams of the light, but ſhall ere long diſcover the very ſun it ſelf. The Truth being thus muffled with errors, hath not yet ſhewn her ſelf to all with a full countenance, although ſhe hath aforehand darted out the rays of her light unto a great part of men. But whatſoever is to come here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, divine things are at preſent envelloped with groſs darkneſs. Yet is there nothing that more obſcureth the Myſtery of Eternal Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then the ignorance of the way, that leadeth us to the top of ſo great happineſs. For as all things ſituated on high, are wont to have a hard and difficult acceſs; ſo alſo hath that towring height of the life to come. Nor is it for every man to get up through ſteep aſcents, eſpecially for them whoſe earthly mindes and dull ſpirits preſs them down to lowe deſires. And therefore, to the great deſtruction of mankinde, another way to happineſs hath heen invented, eaſie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed and expedite, but ſuch as reacheth not to the end aimed at. For the greateſt part of men, thinking it very toilſom to aſcend thither by ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of life, ſought out a ſhorter cut, conſiſting in the meer confeſſion of faith. And this is the way by which the greateſt part as yet aſcend to heaven, not caring what their actions are, ſo their opinions be right; and though extremely curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to pry into other things, yet having no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to their life and maners. So that it is no marvel, inaſmuch as men everywhere take grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter care of their wit, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of their minde, that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115483:8"/>
the very leaſt failing in the knowledge of divine things ſhould be eſteemed of greater moment to eternal deſtruction, then then the commiſſion of the fouleſt crimes. But this ſeemeth ſomewhat monſtrous, how ſome men ſhould arrive at ſo much confidence, as that, though in their life and maners they even againſt their wills acknowledg the failings of their mortality, yet in their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and opinions they ſhould forget their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: and though in the very ſoul of faith, I mean good works, they do by reaſon of their ſins ſo often ſlip, ſhould yet imagine that in the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe onely, I mean faith, they cannot poſſibly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend. For, whence proceedeth this blinde and precipitant humour of condemning others, but from raſhneſs of defining? whence ſo great bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of determining, but from the preſumption of an infallible judgement? And, which is worſt of all, a man now-a-days can no ſooner fail in his wit, but preſently his honeſty is reproached; and oftentimes the reprehenſion of opinions degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateth into the accuſation of maners. As for my ſelf, before I lanch out of the haven, I do alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy foreſee ſtorms; nor am I in ſo great fear for the Opinion which I propoſe in this Diſcourſe, as for my credit and ſecurity. For how few are there who will cenſure this Treatiſe, without do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing injury to the Author? who is there, that will ſet a mark on ſome miſtake thereof, and not withal brand me with ſome reproach? If any thing here ſhall ſeem falſe to ſome men, they will account me not onely a lyer, but an impious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. They will call me Deceiver, and Patron of damned Hereſie; and this writing will be ſo fifty-cuffed by many, that I my ſelf perhaps, were
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115483:8"/>
I known, ſhould not eſcape Scot-free. But my minde being pure and untainted, will from my conſcience reap that fruit of my labour, which was due to it from the judgements of men: nor will I eſteem it a weak argument of having de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended the Truth, to have my innocencie ſo wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly traduced. For the ſame ſpirit is wont to oppoſe both of them: nor ought it to ſeem ſtrange to any man, that a moſt true Opinion ſhould be unjuſtly taxed of error, when he ſhall ſee his own innocencie circumvented with falſe accuſations. Nevertheleſs I inſtantly beſeech them, who after they have read this Diſcourſe, ſhall vote concerning my reputation, that they would not charge me with other mens faults; and that my harmleſs freedom may not be any prejudice to me. Let none impute to me the patronage of Error, if I have perhaps been fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable unto ſuch as erre; unleſs he ſuppoſe it to be the duty of a man, when he is diſpleaſed with the vices, to be angry with the perſons alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:115483:9"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>What things concerning God and Christ are neceſſary to be known unto Salvation; and what are the parts of true Faith.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe whole body of the Church hath now for a long time been infeſted with an evil ſpirit, which ſets the ſeveral members at oddes amongſt themſelves. Certainly it is obſtinate Ambition that cheriſheth the humor of raiſing parties, and much oyl is poured on this flame by a vain per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion concerning the points in controverſie, that in each of them the ſum of our Religion lies at ſtake. How deeply this opinion hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken root in our mindes, is evident from the Civil wars amongſt us, whereby our hatred turneth to our mutual ruine. But how frivolous and falſe it is, ſhall plainly appear from what we mean to ſpeak afterwards; wherein to examine all things that come into debate, would be a long and toyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome buſineſs. It is ſufficient to cull-out one of the chiefeſt points, which if we ſhall evince not to be neceſſarily required to the attainment of eternal Happineſs, much leſs will it be true in the other lighter ones. And this is an exact knowledge of the Divine Eſſence, (as they term it) and a diſtinct explication of the Holy Trinity. Undoubtedly no man can comprehend the nature of God, and the reſtleſs diſpoſition of our minde doth here in vain beſtir it ſelf, to reach ſo high a myſtery in this life. We may indeed by our Reaſon very
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115483:9"/>
eaſily ſeparate not onely defects, but alſo the very ſhadow of imperfection from ſo great a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, but to form in our minde an image worthy of that moſt noble Eſſence, is beyond the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs of our mortality. And conſequently, we may and ought to know what it is not: but to know what it is, though we were never ſo much bound to it, yet are we not able; unleſs perhaps that God is the King and Lord of the Univerſe, and other ſuch-like things, which if we ſpeak pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, belong not to his eſſence. It cannot be denied, that ſome of theſe things are diſcovered to us by the ſacred Oracles, but they are very few, and ſome of them onely ſhadowed out with obſcure lineaments: and if there be any, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in all Chriſtians are not agreed, they are at this day enwrapped with ſo many twiſted thorns of Sophiſters, and alſo heretofore diſcuſſed with ſo much wrangling, that they are as yet doubted-of by many. Adde hereunto the probable allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Scriptures on both ſides, ſo that if one will hear both parties without prejudice, he will not for the moſt part eaſily rid himſelf out of ſo great intricacies. It is not my purpoſe to ſtretch mine own wit, to engage in diſpute on ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide. It is ſufficient if I demonſtrate, <hi>that thoſe questions that concern the more ſpecial explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Divine Eſſence, and the accurate diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Perſons, although they be never ſo profitable, yet are not neceſſary to ſalvation:</hi> or, which is all one, <hi>that a Chriſtian may arrive at the promiſed goal of happineſs, although he be either ignorant of thoſe things, or (ſuch is the condition of our weakneſs) in an error or miſtake about them.</hi> If Error in theſe things taketh not away ſalvation, much leſs Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115483:10"/>
And therefore, that there may be no ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity in this Diſcourſe, we will at preſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt onely on the former.</p>
               <p>When I conſider the way that bringeth us to heaven, methinks ſuch contemplations as theſe are out of the road of our journey. For indeed, what maketh us ſufficiently, yea abundantly fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for Eternal life, but Faith working by Love, for which onely we ſhall be pronounced juſt? But if one may have this Faith, although he have a wrong conceit touching the Myſtery of the Holy Trinity, what hinders but that he may together with this Errour be received both into Heaven, and into the Church? Now leſt any one ſhould be deceived in the notion of Error, I do not now give ſo milde a name to their wickedneſs, who whilſt the Truth was yet clear and open in the Church, and called into doubt by none, did firſt ſpread darkneſs over this Article; but to their failing; who in our times</p>
               <p>Do fear the Greeks even when they offer Gifts: that is, who having been cozened with ſo many lyes and cheats of Antichriſt, dare not believe him even when he ſeemeth to ſpeak Truth: as ſhall be further made appear by the ſequele of the Diſcourſe. Moreover, that perfit Faith is not taken away by that error, we ſhall eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, if we enquire into every part thereof. Nor verily ſhall you finde in the whole compaſs of our Faith, that more duties are required of belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, then Aſſent to the Promiſes of Jeſus Chriſt, and Obedience to his Precepts. The firſt of which the Apoſtle <hi>James,</hi> chap. 2. very aptly inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mateth to be the Body of Faith; and the ſecond, the Soul thereof. To the belief of the Promiſes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115483:10"/>
that plain Confeſſion is ſufficient, which paſſeth under the name of <hi>The Apostles Creed:</hi> and if there be any thing elſe requiſite, I ſee not what can be added, beſides the Reverence due to the holy Scriptures, to which if credence be once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed, the certainty of our Salvation is brought into danger. Now whether both, or one of theſe compleat the whole nature of that Faith, which is due to the Divine Promiſes, certainly experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence it ſelf teſtifieth, that ſuch as erre in the knowledge of the foreſaid Myſtery, may excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently diſcharge this part of Faith. For they without any exception give credence to the holy Scripture, and to the Apoſtles Creed. And therefore what is wanting to beget in them a full belief, that God cannot chuſe but perform his promiſe? For, that the things aforeſaid are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to the belief hereof, is even from hence manifeſt. God hath promiſed us Salvation by his Son. To rely on this promiſe, it is enough if we be perſwaded, that God both can and will give unto us what he hath promiſed. For by this means all the cauſes of diſtruſt being pared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, there will be no ground left to doubt of ſo great a Promiſe. But whilſt they believe the holy Scriptures, and their Abridgement the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Creed, they cannot in the leaſt doubt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the power or will of God; when not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they may miſtake in the knowledge of his Eſſence. Wherefore this firſt part of Faith is not taken away by that Error. As for Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Precepts of Chriſt, certainly this can much leſs be taken away by ſuch miſtakings. For neither was it the purpoſe of God, by giving his Commandments to exerciſe the ſharpneſs of our
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115483:11"/>
Wit, but the goodneſs of our Will. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how blinde ſoever our Knowledge is in ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſer things, yet may our Will be conformed to the obedience of the Divine Law, then which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more manifeſt and open. Nor doth the Piety of ſundry erring perſons here need an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vcoate, in that it ſufficiently pleadeth for it ſelf, and oftentimes ſheweth its Faith even in ſilent works, which very many vainly boaſting of, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not finde in their life and actions. Neither indeed hath any thing been enjoyned us, wherein our vertue and obedience may not ſhew themſelves. For what need is there to invite us with rewards to thoſe things, which we willingly perform of our own accord? But they buy Happineſs at a very cheap rate, who ſpend nothing but the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of their Wit upon it. For he that is never ſo wicked and careleſs of his Salvation, may know ſome truth concerning God. Nor can we boaſt of our obedience in ſuch things, unleſs we admit the damned Spirits to a ſhare in our praiſe. Beſides, the nature of all Precepts ought to be ſuch, as that it might evidently appear to all, who are to perform them, that they are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed. But how manifeſt this doctrine touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Trinity is, the incredible height of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing it ſelf ſheweth; and how manifeſtly it is preſcribed, the labours and contentions of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Fathers and Councels heretofore teſtifie. Yea, though ſomthing in this point were never ſo much enjoyned to be known and believed, yet none re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth to believe thoſe things, that are expreſly extant in the holy Scriptures: nor is there any one ſo impious as to contradict them. All the controverſie is about meanings and conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115483:11"/>
wherein an error and failing doth no more infer diſobedience, and conſequently damnation, then the ſimplicity of an obſequious ſervant, who not rightly underſtanding the command of his Maſter, did yet obey as far as he was able. But if we may believe the Promiſes of Jeſus Chriſt, and obey his Precepts, although we are miſtaken in ſuch a maner, what ſhall we want to the full poſſeſſion of a lively Faith? Is there yet any thing in the nature of Faith, uncomprehended in thoſe two parts? But there is a wonderful ſilence in the Sacred Oracles concerning that third part; nor do I ſee how that Faith is not perfit, which is lively; or how that is not lively, which conſiſteth in a maner of its body and ſoul. But you will ſay, that we are neceſſarily to believe many things, which are neither the very Precepts, nor the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes. To which I anſwer, that they ſo belong to one of theſe, that without them neither can be rightly performed; of which ſort is the Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencie of God, and the like attributes, as alſo the Creation, Providence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which though they be neither the Precepts, nor the Promiſes, yet can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not the belief of the Promiſes conſiſt without them; ſo that an error in them is not now dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, but altogether peſtilent and pernicious. But it hath been clearly proved that errors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thoſe doctrines, touching which the whole Diſcourſe hath been ſet on foot, ſubvert neither member of Faith, at leaſt in their own nature, and unavoidably.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:115483:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>That ſincere Love towards God and Christ is ſufficient to Salvation; and that the ſame may be in ſuch as erre.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LEt us adde an Appendix to this argument, which may even be in ſtead of a new reaſon. Who therefore dares to condemn him to the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of Eternal Death, in whom liveth the ſincere Love of his Creator and Redeemer? or what more certain pledge of Eternal Happineſs is there, then to love God and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, with the whole heart, and with all the powers of the minde? This indeed is too too manifeſt, inaſmuch as the ſum of our Obedience lieth herein, which though it be not the cauſe of our Salvation, yet is it at leaſt the way, and an evident argument and moſt certain ſigne there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Now if it ſhall be made plainly to appear, that they, who are not able to extricate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out of thoſe perplexed and craggie Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, whereof we have ſpoken, may notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in the mean time love God and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, with all the powers of their minde; what cauſe will there be, why we ſhould not think that the ſame perſons may be ſaved? Logicians ſay, that the next and immediate cauſe (as they term it) cannot be hindered, but it will out of hand produce the effect. Let us therefore in the firſt place conſider the next cauſe of this Love; and then we ſhall ſee whether it may be in men ſo erring.</p>
               <p>The perfit Love of any one is bred in the minds
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115483:12"/>
of the lovers chiefly for three cauſes concurring together. 1. From the firm and conſtant me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of ſuch benefits as are paſt, and from the ſenſe of ſuch as are preſent. For gratitude alſo is a part of Love. 2. From a certain hope and confidence of Supreme Happineſs to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained from the beloved thing, if you come to enjoy it. For love languiſheth without deſire. 3. And finally, from a perfit apprehenſion, as far as may be, of the ſoverain beauty and excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the object: which is the true and principal cauſe of the Love it ſelf. Now foraſmuch as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the perfit Love of God, nor the perfit per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of his Excellencie can fully happen to us in this life: we mean not an abſolute perfection of both, but ſuch as is the chiefeſt in its kinde, namely as great as can exiſt in this ſtate of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality. Nor do I underſtand, what can be further required unto perfit love. For who ſeeth not, that our will can no more abſtain from loving a perceived beauty, then fire from burning ſtubble put unto it? Which beauty, if it be perfitly ſeen, a perfit love alſo will ariſe: but if no more then perfitly in its kinde, a love alſo perfit it its kinde will ariſe. Certainly if any one denyeth that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verain Love neceſſarily proceedeth from ſuch a cauſe, he ſubverteth the Principles of Nature, which dictateth even to children, that whatſoever ſeemeth good or beautiful, will alſo prove very pleaſing; and ſo Love will be increaſed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the meaſure of the apprehended beauty. It remaineth that we conſider, whether ſuch a perfit perception of the Excellencie of God and his Chriſt, accompanied with thoſe two helping cauſes, may not be in them, who comprehend not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115483:13"/>
thoſe hidden and abſtruſe Myſteries of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence. Which if it be in us who do not erre, it may alſo be in them, or it will be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to ſhew a reaſon of the Prerogative which we have above them in this behalf. And firſt, let us ſpeak of God the Father. As for the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his favours, they acknowledge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves together with us to be obliged unto him, perpetually making mention of his infinite mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; the chiefeſt whereof conſiſteth in taking us for his children. As for the certain expectation of a very great benefit, what vaſter hope, what laviſher wiſh can be fained, then that which they together with us deſire and expect from the moſt high God? There remaineth behinde the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of his beauty and majeſtie. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs there is nothing in humane matters ſo exact, that can lend a ſhadow to the image of ſo great a Majeſty. Nevertheleſs as touching God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they do in a maner agree with us. For we are able to conceive nothing ſo great and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime touching him, which they alſo do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive. Nor doth it follow, that becauſe they do not reach the curious ſubtilty in the received diſtinction of Perſons, therefore they cannot ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their capacity conceive the beauty of the Divine Countenance, not to be ſeen by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane mindes; and conſequently dedicate and worſhip the image of that unſpeakable Majeſty within the Sanctuary of their breaſt. As if it were a hard matter to have all maner of high concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions touching him, whom you certainly know and continually think to be the ſource and origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of all goodneſs and beauty, although you do not comprehend doctrines ſnarled and entangled
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115483:13"/>
with ſo many knots. Enough ſeemeth to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſpoken touching God the Father. But what if they have like, yea the ſame cauſes with us of Love towards the Son of God, will any thing hinder them from being as capable of this love as we our ſelves are? Let us begin from Hope. Do not they expect the ſame bountiful right hand of the Lord Jeſus, which will hereafter reach out a heavenly reward to all the faithful? Do they not luxuriate in this wiſh? And who can chuſe but feel his heart wounded with the love of Chriſt, who ſetteth Chriſt before his eyes as giving him the pay of his warfare? But you will ſay, that in making an eſtimate of his favours they ſeem to be injurious to him, whilſt they affirm, that the Fathers anger towards us was appeaſed without the entermiſe of Chriſt, and that no price, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſo called, was paid for our ſins. For I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that almoſt all, who in the article of the Holy Trinity diſſent from us, are of that opinion. I defend not the opinion of the men, neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs I perceive that they judge a Redemption, properly ſo called, to be both abſurd, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible. What derogation therefore is it either to gratitude towards the Lord Jeſus, or to the holy memory of his merits, if they imagine that he did not thoſe things for our ſakes, which could at no hand be done; when in the mean time he abundantly performed all other things which might proceed from him toward us? For no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing is required to the moſt ſtrict obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a benefit, then that the benefactor do for ones ſake all that he is able. But they acknowledg that the Lord Jeſus did for our ſalvation ſpare no pains, yea not his very life. And though they
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115483:14"/>
do not think that his blood was ſpilt to appeaſe God, and therefore not ſo rigidly to make ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for our ſins, yet do they hold that it was ſpent and given for our ſakes; ſo that although they aſſert another ſpecial ſcope and effect of his death, then we do, nevertheleſs they ſeem to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the ſame merit in general. And who would not be imbued with a moſt tender affection towards him, whom he ſuppoſeth to have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone a moſt bitter death for his life's ſake? who would not moſt ardently love him, whom he thinketh perpetually buſied in conferring bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits upon him? To which if you adde an expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of Supreme Happineſs from his hands, it cannot now happen otherwiſe but that the minde ſhould melt in the reſentment of a moſt delicate flame. I come now to the excellency of the Lord Jeſus, which being imperfitly conceived by them, ſeemeth unable to excite a perfit love of it ſelf. For how great a diminution is it of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and nobility, to have all that taken away from him, which he had from all eternity? The queſtion is not now, whether their opinion be right, who think that all power both in heaven and earth was at a certain time given to the Son of God, whereas he was formerly nothing but the <hi>Word</hi> and chief Prophet. But if true Love be converſant about the things that are preſent, and not about ſuch as are paſt, (for neither doth this affection look backwards, to embrace the things that have been heretofore) certainly it is more to the purpoſe to conſider, what they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine touching his preſent, then what they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive touching his paſt ſtate and condition. For as beauty, being quite extinct, exciteth no love
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115483:14"/>
of it ſelf, becauſe it flouriſhed heretofore: ſo if the ſame be at preſent very happie, it cauſeth never the leſs love &amp; admiration of it ſelf, becauſe it was not ſuch formerly. What therefore do they attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to our Saviour at preſent? Even a majeſty equal unto God the Father, and ſuch excellency as riſeth-up above the higheſt pitch that can be imagined. For they ſerve and worſhip him as the onely Son of God, as a true God, and diſpoſing all things with his beck; who deſcribeth the laws of the Univerſe according to his pleaſure; who layeth tasks and commands upon the bleſſed Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of heaven; who with the bridle of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible power reſtraineth the ſpirits baniſhed out of heaven; to whom the ſtars and elements willingly yield obedience, and who finally hath the very nature of things tributary to him, from whence he levyeth the tax of his Church, and the aſſeſment of his people. Now what deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is it to his honour, that he is beholding to his Father for the fortune of ſo great a Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion? which thing even we our ſelves dare not wholly deny. Will the opinion touching the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of our Saviour flag in the judgement of our love, when we ſhall erect the eyes of our minde to his ſo ſublime majeſtie, who is fairer then the ſtars and all light, and more gay then the world it ſelf? Why ſhould I now comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morate his immenſe goodneſs and wiſdom, and his other Divine Splendor, at the ſight whereof the eyes of our minde grow dim? Why ſhould I recount his other praiſes, at which the poverty of humane language waxeth dumb? All which they without any tergiverſation aſcribe to Jeſus Chriſt their Saviour, although they otherwiſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115483:15"/>
erre in their opinion of him. Now we muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hold that thoſe things are not ſufficient to excite ſoverain love towards God the Father, and his Son: or that they cannot poſſibly be in thoſe men, of whom we treat, if we ſuppoſe them uncapable of being touched with that holy ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour. Of which twain ſince neither ſeemeth probable, there is no queſtion to be made, but they alſo may be raviſhed with that heavenly love, and ſo delivered from eternal deſtruction, and put in poſſeſſion of heaven, if ſo be they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere therein unto the end.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII. <hi>That though Faith and the Holy Spirit be the Gifts of God, yet erring perſons have and may have them.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YEt ſome body may juſtly make a doubt, if Faith be the gift of God, and ſuch a perfit and entire love ought to proceed onely from the impulſion of the Holy Spirit, with what warrant we attribute that to the power of the receiver, which lieth in the meer pleaſure of the donor. For if we have Faith no other way then from the liberality of God, and that happeneth not to every one, certainly the benefit of ſo great a gift conſiſteth in the meer good-pleaſure of the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ificent donor. Now ſhall we little manikins pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe a law to his moſt free arbitrement, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the form whereof he muſt of neceſſity make good this bounty of his to a certain ſort of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115483:15"/>
men? Or ſhall we arrogate that to our power, which the ſacred Oracles place in his hand? But is it credible that he will laviſh out ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent gifts, (I ſpeak of Faith and the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit) on men depraved with ſo many errors, and imbued with perverſe opinions concerning him? Admit they are naturally capable of ſo great a good, yet ought they not preſently to promiſe to themſelves this grace of God, which no man, that was in his wits, did ever imagine to be due to the deſerts of men, much leſs to the perverſneſs of ſo many errors. To which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: Had I to do with none but them, who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all action of our free reception from the donation of Faith, or imagine that Eternal Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is in good earneſt promiſed to fewer, then it is outwardly offered, it would be ſutable to handle theſe matters in this place more largely. But now foraſmuch as not a few of the Reformed abhor thoſe errors, it would croſs the deſigne of my diſcourſe to digreſs and expatiate very far. It ſhall ſuffice to have touched a few, and thoſe not of the beſt arguments for the truer opinion, but ſuch as firſt occur at preſent. In the firſt place therefore we muſt chuſe one of theſe twain, either to imagine that Eternal Salvation is upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Faith really promiſed unto all, to whom it is preached and offered; or that God offers that to certain men in word and tongue, which he hath decreed not to perform in deed and truth. Whoſoever ſhall make choice of the latter, I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat them that they would invent a new name for this thing, or confeſs it under the old name to be hypocriſie, that is, guileful diſſimulation and deceit, what they imprudently aſcribe to the moſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115483:16"/>
high God. But I have little to do with ſuch, as had rather God ſhould be taxed and convinced of evil diſſembling, then themſelves of error: and therefore I lay this firſt ground of my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; that God is faithful, and willing ſeriouſly to give Eternal Happineſs, to whomſoever he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth the ſame by the preaching of the Goſpel, unleſs men themſelves be wanting to their duty. But he hath excluded none of thoſe, to whoſe ears the voice of ſo joyful a meſſage cometh, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to gather even them that are unwilling, if ſo be they leave off their unwillingneſs. Now if God in the preaching of the Goſpel hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Eternal Salvation promiſcuouſly to all, who deſire to attain it, he hath alſo promiſed all means tending to this end, which are on his part neceſſarily required. For he would be ridiculous, who ſhould promiſe to a begger that he would preſently give him an alms, and in the mean time be careleſs, yea unwilling to put his hand to his purſe, that he may reach-out what he hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, eſpecially if the begger can receive that alms no other way then by his reaching of it out. Nor can he be ſaid truly to promiſe any thing, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth to himſelf a free power to beſtow ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, without which what he hath promiſed can by no means be received and acquired. Far be it from us to have ſo impious a thought towards God, as that we ſhould ſuſpect any evil concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the reality of his Words. To whomſoever he hath promiſed any thing, he hath truely and ſincerely promiſed it, nor will he circumvent any ones credulity with any ſlights and put-offs. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing drove him to the indulgence of ſo great a benefit, but his own good will towards mankinde.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115483:16"/>
Wherefore he is favourable to his own gifts, and leaveth no impediment to them, ſo that now no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be wanting on his part to the attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them, which he doth not willingly impart to all. Whereby it cometh to paſs, that the gift of Faith, and whatſoever God conferreth to the office of believers, although it be, like the very Salvation it ſelf, free and voluntary, and no ways deſerved, yet is it denyed to none, who having heard the conditions of the New Covenant, doth willingly aſſent to them, and is not wanting to himſelf in ſo great mercy of God: which I would have alſo underſtood concerning all ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual gifts, without which his promiſe cannot be acquired. For I will not deny that there are ſome, to the promiſcuous beſtowing whereof he hath engaged his faith to none; which lying out of the direct road that leadeth to the kingdom of heaven, are not pertinent to the thing in hand. But the conditions which are on Gods part re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to the nature of the New Covenant, are already, or ſhall certainly be fulfilled by God: all that remaineth is, that the other party will be mindful of ſo holy a ſtipulation, and both believe and obey this Covenant. Which latter, ſince it may agree to this ſort of men, whereof we ſpeak, as hath been made evident from the precedent diſcourſe, what is there lacking unto them, being compriſed in this tranſaction of God with men, to the full freedom and property of all the gifts and promiſes? For the errors of the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, eſpecially in things not concerning the very nature of the Covenant, cannot hinder them from reaping the fruit thereof, in that (as we have Already ſhewn) the knowledge of thoſe things
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115483:17"/>
is out of the conditions of the Covenant, (that is, lively Faith and Obedience) and therefore may be abſent, and depraved, whilſt in the mean time thoſe conditions remain entire. But of theſe things we will more largely treat in the enſuing Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>That nothing but Diſobedience and Unbelief exclude a man from Eternal Salvation; and that ſuch as erre, are free from theſe. Whether bare Errors of the Underſtanding damn a man.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHat it is lawful for almighty God to do to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards mankinde, is queſtioned by none, that is not ignorant of his abſolute dominion. What he is willing and wont to do, and how he ordereth and guideth his commands, and the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth of the world, with rewards and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties, is a thing right worthy to be taken into conſideration. Certainly we are all born in a Kingdom, which is by the goodneſs of the moſt high God made ſo milde and pleaſant to us, that all the ſweetneſs of liberty is ſordid in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thereof. But he ſheweth himſelf a Father, in ſtead of a Lord and Prince, unto a great part of men, of which alone we will at preſent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. For we who have heard the voice of his Promiſes, are all called from the meanneſs of our rank to the condition of the Divine Adoption.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115483:17"/>
To enjoy ſo great felicity as it is happy: ſo to miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it is very wretched and calamitous. It therefore very much concerneth men, to foreſee by what ſteps they may be tumbled down from ſo great a height. And they who have already got-up ſo high, that they have a hope of Eternal Salvation upon the conditions of the New Covenant, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be pulled down from their ſtation but by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief and diſobedience. For ſince in this laſt Covenant nothing is required of us beſides a lively Faith, concerning which we have formerly ſpoken, certainly we can by no other means vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the Holy Engagement of that compact, then if we become deſtitute of that very faith, which cannot be done without the crime of manifeſt diſobedience. For it is enjoyned and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded us, unleſs we had rather periſh. And what elſe is faith then obedience to God under a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain hope and confidence of his promiſes? As <hi>Abraham</hi> being called obeyed by faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. wherefore if this one rock of diſobedience be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided, we have no cauſe to fear the ſhipwrack of our ſalvation. It now remaineth to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, whether bare errors of the minde are diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience. That they are not ſo, is even from hence apparent, becauſe they conſiſt in the miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the underſtanding, but this in the pravity of the will. Again, ſince God regardeth not the actions themſelves, but the minde of the agents, who ſeeth not that they who deſiring from their hearts to obey, yet through error and imprudence do not ſo, cannot be juſtly accuſed of diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? A ſervant doth not refuſe his ſervice, if not rightly apprehending his maſters will, he ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filleth it according to his underſtanding; much
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115483:18"/>
leſs may he be puniſhed for diſobedience, and that with eternal puniſhment. Nor doth God ſo much regard the effect as the decree of our counſel. And if you look to the event of the thing, neither did <hi>Abraham</hi> indeed obey God, commanding to ſacrifice his ſon <hi>Iſaac,</hi> yet did he obey in his heart and minde. For he was willing to obey God, and did all he could, being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited by the Angel to do the reſt, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22. Suppoſe it to be commanded that we believe the true explication of the Holy Trinity. Such as ſimply erre do not indeed obey this precept, for they diſſent from ſuch as are orthodox, yet do they obey in their minde and heart, becauſe they are willing to believe, and do believe all that which they think to be true, although they do not hit in all things the genuine ſenſe of that which is true. And ſo they do what they are able, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hindered by ignorance from doing more. But you will ſay, that ignorance is groſs and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected. I excuſe not that which is affected, ſuch as was in them, who whilſt the Apoſtles were living, or their ſucceſſors, did erre willingly and of ſet purpoſe. For this was meer malice. But they who after ſo great darkneſs had beſpread the Church, do not diſcern the riſing light from counterfeit torches, cannot be ſaid to ſin out of malice and through their own fault, as ſhall alſo hereafter be more largely handled. But what if it hath been ſhewn that it is not commanded, nor pertaineth to the nature of our faith and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? Shall they preſently be diſobedient, who do not fully underſtand a myſtery, which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where commanded to be fully underſtood? In ſhort, whether they, who are called <hi>Socinians,</hi> do
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115483:18"/>
ſin out of a bare error of minde, we ſhall ſee hereafter. It is ſufficient for me at preſent to evince, that bare errors of minde are not puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God with eternal puniſhment under the New Covenant. Elegant is that of <hi>Bernard, Nothing burns in Hell, but our own will.</hi> For it onely is capable of receiving the filthineſs of ſin: for which in the whole Univerſe there had been no place, unleſs God had left to intelligent crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures a free and entire will. Unleſs (I ſay) God had diſcharged the will from all condition of ſervitude, all proof of vertue had periſhed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the licenſe of ſinning. Although ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry many had rather acknowledge God the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of ſin, then the bounteous giver of this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. Of which liberty notwithſtanding it is an evident ſigne, that we abuſe it alone to the licenſe of ſinning: ſo that the failing of our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding deſervedly ſeemeth worthy of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeration and pardon, whereas the pravity of our will deſerveth hatred and puniſhment. It is therefore no wonder if God puniſheth this, rather then the other, with eternal deſtruction; becauſe in this there is place for guilt, in the other onely for imbecillity. But he never puniſhed imbecillity and ignorance for contumacie, eſpecially with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme and everlaſting puniſhment. Likewiſe in the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> whereof he was ſo ſevere an exactor, as that he ratified the reverence of one ceremony with the blood of a man that went to gather ſticks, <hi>Num.</hi> 15. yet did he leave pardon for error, and a refuge for ignorance, and that in the moſt grievous crimes, which concern the life and ſafety of a man. The rigor of the <hi>Moſaick</hi> Law pardoneth his offence who killed a man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115483:19"/>
and granteth him a repeal after the death of the High-Prieſt. And why ſhould not alſo the lenity of the Chriſtian Covenant abſolve the fault of ſuch as erre, after the death of Chriſt our High-Prieſt, whoſe yoke is ſweet, and burthen light, and who refuſeth not to disburthen and caſe us of the fardle of our ſins? who hath left on record in the latter end of his Teſtament, how worthy he accounted errors of pardon, whilſt in the moſt cruel nick of his death he prayed for thoſe that erred, <hi>Luke</hi> 23. Indeed to pray for them who ſin unto death, it is not lawful: nor would the Lord ever have done that amidſt the ſacrilegious boldneſs of ſo great a crime, had he not taken pity on their unhappie ignorance. <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them,</hi> ſaith he. For what reaſon? Becauſe <hi>they know not what they do.</hi> Now if in the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſo great a murder there remained, even in our Saviours judgement, ſome place for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, ſhall we with our cenſures damn to eternal puniſhment the meer clouds of the minde, and harmleſs ignorance? But you will ſay, Shall we hold that ignorance and errors are never pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with everlaſting deſtruction? What ſhall become of the ſouls of ſo many thouſand Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels? what of thoſe barbarous Braſilians, and others of that ſort, the greateſt part whereof have not had ſo much as a ſuſpicion touching God and Chriſt? Shall we ſay that theſe ſhall be puniſhed for contumacie, who know not any law, from whoſe obedience they may revolt? Shall not the ignorance of God and Chriſt in them undergo everlaſting puniſhment? In the firſt place, I deny that they are in any ſort pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, to whoſe ears the ſound of the ſaving do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115483:19"/>
never came, and ſay that they are onely left in that wretched condition, to which they were liable by their very birth. For inaſmuch as the puniſhment of our firſt parent derived the moſt wretched ſtate of eternal death to his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, God might according to his wiſdom and good-pleaſure exempt whom he would from this miſery, leaving the reſt in the ſame. For who ſhall preſcribe a law to his abſolute power? or ſet bounds to his clemency? Thoſe therefore, to whom he hath revealed his law, he puniſheth as rebels, unleſs they obey, not with any new kinde of puniſhment, (eſpecially after death) but onely by leaving them in their miſerable ſtate together with the reſt. Others, to whom he hath not vouchſafed ſo great a benefit, he leaveth indeed in the ſame ſtate, but doth not therefore puniſh. For the reaſon of eternal death, as it is to be called a puniſhment, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth not in the appointment of a new puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but in a certain ademption of the Divine Grace, which might free them out of the ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the old puniſhment; which certainly is not taken away from them, to whom it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver offered. But ſome one will reply, Why ſhould thoſe wretched Ignorants be in the ſame condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the impious and diſobedient? As if God were unjuſt towards thoſe, becauſe he uſeth clemency towards theſe. Doth the Lord of the vine yard do wrong to the labourers, when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſeth the unequal merits of ſundry perſons with one reward, not by taking ſomewhat away from them that were more deſerving, but onely by adding ſomewhat to them that were leſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving? <hi>Mat.</hi> 20. But if ſomething may be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115483:20"/>
added to their reward, who are leſs deſerving, without wrong to thoſe who are more deſerving; ſomething alſo may be taken away from their puniſhment, who are more deſerving, without wrong to them who are leſs deſerving. Suppoſe that one hath promiſed liberty to <hi>Titius</hi> his ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptive upon a certain condition, without promiſing any thing to <hi>Sejus. Titius</hi> for his contumacie loſeth the reward, receiving nothing from his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, but remaining captive and miſerable toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>Sejus.</hi> Can <hi>Sejus</hi> now complain, that he being innocent, endureth the ſame things with <hi>Titius</hi> who was diſobedient? <hi>Titius</hi> may rather acknowledge the clemencie of his maſter, who would content himſelf with the meer ademption of the reward. As therefore innocent <hi>Sejus</hi> is not puniſhed by his maſter, although he be left in the ſame miſery with guilty <hi>Titius:</hi> ſo neither ſhall the ignorant <hi>Braſilians</hi> be hereafter puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by not receiving that which was never promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to them. Theſe may rather ponder on the grievous puniſhment of their contumacie, who ſee their Salvation, and pine away for having forſaken it. We have, I ſuppoſe, ſhewn ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, that ſuch Ignorants, whereof we ſpeak, are not puniſhed. But if we grant that they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo are puniſhed, ſhall they be preſently puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for their ignorance? As if that ignorance were that which ought to be puniſhed, and is not it ſelf rather a certain puniſhment. Who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not that God oftentimes avengeth wickedneſs and crimes with errors? Who would not reckon ſuch ignorance amongſt the horrid puniſhments of God? This therefore will remain to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired further, for what cauſes he hath puniſhed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115483:20"/>
them with ſo great blindneſs? But who hath known the thoughts of the Lord? or who hath been his counſellour? There is no cauſe why any one ſhould fiſh this ſecret out of me, but that I certainly know that God proceedeth ſlowly and unwillingly to puniſhment, and that every one is undoubtedly the author of his own deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Of all them that were wicked and inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded under ſin, the moſt high God might take pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty on ſome, and puniſh others. So that the cauſe of this puniſhment ſhould, as it ſeemeth, be ſought-for, not in the ignorance but the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of men, and in the ſpecial good-pleaſure of the wiſe God. Let us proceed further. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thoſe barbarous Braſilians to be puniſhed for ignorance. What is this to our errors? Their ignorance taketh away all faith, religion, and piety. We ſpeak of the bare errors of the mind, which are ſo far from weakning faith, or religion, that they ought, under the penalty of everlaſting deſtruction, to be free even from all contagion of wickedneſs. Finally, admit that the Braſili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are puniſhed for the bare ignorance of their minde, (which notwithſtanding we do not grant) ſhall we therefore ſay that the ſame ignorance is puniſhed by God with ſo grievous and bitter a puniſhment in our erroneous ones? The puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe doth infinitely differ from the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of theſe. It is an eaſie matter to loſe ſuch things as the minde with a flattering hope never promiſed to it ſelf. The reward of eternal Life is not promiſed to them, no hope of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality given them, no taſte of everlaſting joy of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to them: they never endeavoured to enter in thorow the ſtrait gate; to deny themſelves;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115483:21"/>
they have not attempted to bear their croſs; to follow their Saviour thorow the afflictions of this world. But the greateſt part of them who erre through the bare imbecillity of their wit, have omitted nothing to the moſt certain hope of Salvation, and to all the toyl of a pious life, and to the tolerance of Chriſts croſs. Shall we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that theſe ſhall for their meer ignorance, and the miſtakes of their underſtanding, be diſcarded from the forethought and foretaſted expectation of eternal joy? Shall we think that their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours ſhall be in vain, and their hope and faith vaniſh into ſmoke? Certainly this would be a moſt wretched condition, and not to be compared with that puniſhment of thoſe Barbarians. So that it can at no hand ſeem probable to any man, who ſetteth before his eyes the infinite grace and mercy of God, eſpecially under the new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, that ignorance ſhould have ſo ſevere a puniſhment inflicted on it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:115483:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>That the things neceſſary to be known unto Salvation, are few and very ſimple, and eaſie to be underſtood b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the ſimpleſt. Such is not the common doctrine touching the Trinity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are not wanting ſome, amongſt ſo many families of Chriſtians, who im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gine certain particular men, whom they call Reprobates, to be by name excluded from the Heavenly Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: yet do the opinions of almoſt all diſſenting parties herein agree, that the way to Salvation is beforehand ſhut-up and obſtructed to no ſort of men. And indeed, not without good reaſon. For ſince they are all equal in the ſight of the moſt high God, and no mans dignity exempteth him out of the condition of the reſt, there is no reſpect of perſons with God, no regard of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie. He vieweth not the mindes of men tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row thoſe coverings of the body, or thorow the dreſs and ornament of the outward fortune, but naked and ſequeſtred from all diſguiſes; and therefore the condition, which is for the moſt part without the verge of the man himſelf, ought to difference none before him. As for the counſel therefore of the great God, all are alike deſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Eternal Happineſs, whether they be men or women, yong or old; clad in ſcarlet, or cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer wool; having ſo much land that they cannot count it, or having no land to count; in ſhort,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115483:22"/>
whether they be born to rule, or ſervitude; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe liberal, or manual arts, all are promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and in the ſame degree called to that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Inheritance. How few of all theſe can pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate into thoſe abſtruſer ſecrets of ſublime doctrines? And therefore by the moſt wiſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of God, the heads neceſſary to ſalvation are ſo ordered, that they may without any pains be underſtood and comprehended by all. Howbeit that doctrine, touching which the preſent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is intended, is ſo intricate and hard, and doth ſo far ſurpaſs the apprehenſion of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pler ſort, that very few of them can promiſe Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to themſelves, if it be prejudicial to any one to have a miſunderſtanding of theſe things. For the queſtion is not concerning the Holy Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, which all confeſs and adore, even they who are nicknamed <hi>Samoſatenians,</hi> but touching the difference of Eſſences and Perſons, touching the communication of properties, touching thoſe My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, which no man ever ſaw, nor ſufficiently underſtood. Theſe things riſe-up ſo high above our imbecillity, and ſo great a crop of thorns and bryars ſpringeth up when they begin once to be diſcuſſed, that nature ſeldom produceth ſo happie a wit, as can in good earneſt rid himſelf out of that brake. If any one of the duller ſort (and who ſeemeth acute enough for ſo ſubtil things?) ſtick in thoſe bryars, why ſhould we impute that to his wickedneſs, which is due to the weakneſs of his wit? The very ſublimity of the things, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth their difficulty, as alſo the excellencie of the object, which never was, never will be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by the minde of man. And therefore not long after the Apoſtles times, a great bicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115483:22"/>
about theſe things diſturbed the whole world, and did ſo exerciſe the wits of the Fathers, that after ſo many toils and Councels, neither did all agree with one another, nor every one with himſelf. By ſo much eaſier a task it is to ſearch the Majeſty of God, then comprehend it. Which curioſity, how fatal it proved to the world, let us believe the complaint of <hi>Hilary,</hi> who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth the Biſhops of <hi>France</hi> happie, in that they had neither forged, nor received, nor known any other Confeſſion, then that old and moſt ſimple one, which had from the age of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles been received in all Churches. O that we had rather be happie with thoſe <hi>French</hi> Biſhops, then by being over-wiſe diſturb the quiet of the Church, or baniſh out of heaven ſuch ſouls as are incapable of ſo great Myſteries! How many men truely pious and ſimple ſhall you finde, who are not able to maintain and defend their own o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, though ſometimes true? If theſe happen to doubt of the truth, or through imprudencie to ſlip in ſuch matters, ſhall they preſently be exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the entrance both of Heaven and the Church, as enemies of God and Chriſt? What ſhall the wretches do, whilſt oftentimes they hang in ſuſpenſe between a great ſhew of probability on both ſides? And why ſhould not the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſuch things, as are altogether requiſite to Salvation, be as obvious to the ſimple, as to learned wits? Hath God paved an eaſier way to Salvation for the learned and ingenious, then for others? Nor is it very material, that the ruder ſort may apprehend by the teaching of the more learned, what they perhaps cannot of themſelves attain unto. For ſince amongſt the learned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115483:23"/>
there are ſo many controverſies, either the ruder ſort ſhall judge of them by their own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, which is all one, (for it is as hard to determine between the arguments on both ſides, as between true and falſe opinions) or ſhall hand over head follow the authority of others. But if the choice of the true opinion exceedeth their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, ſo that they are altogether enforced to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low others without any premiſed deliberation; what fault of theirs will it be, when they are miſtaken? Therefore they ſhall either be puniſhed guiltleſs for the fault of others, or if they periſh guilty, their onely offence will be this, namely, that they are ſomewhat dull; which is ridiculous. For let us ſuppoſe, what often cometh to paſs, that there are certain ſimple men of an innocent life, and who according to the power of their mortality live piouſly and devoutly: let us alſo ſuppoſe, what often falleth out, that there are learned and ingenious men, but overwhelmed with ſins and treſpaſſes. In both perhaps God may finde juſt cauſe of puniſhment: but he ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not ſo high an eſtimate on wits, as to deal more ſeverely with better men onely for their rudeneſs, then with the worſt of men, and ſuch as by their very ingratitude for his gifts provoke his vengeance. But he ſhould deal more ſeverely with better men, were a certain and infallible way to Salvation quite ſhut up to them for the dulneſs of their wit; and onely an uncertain, and ſlippery one, depending on anothers wit or piety, left them. And if, on the contrary, wicked men, ſo they be ingenious, have always (if they pleaſe) a priviledge to go thorow the right and ſaying path. But you will ſay, God is bound
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115483:23"/>
to none, and when he findeth in both a cauſe of juſt ſeverity, though not equal, he may accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his own good pleaſure proſecute his right in thoſe, and pardon theſe their greater ſins. I anſwer: What God may do, is not here ſo much queſtioned, as what he will, and is wont to do. And therefore though we ſhould grant, that he may do this, yet would it not as yet appear, that he will, and is wont to do ſo. For God may do many things towards men, without impeachment to his juſtice, which otherwiſe his wonted mercy ſeemeth not to permit. But would not a reſpect of perſons be by this means apparently aſcribed unto God, if before him learned men ſhould be in a better condition, then ſimple ones? And yet notwithſtanding he is wont to reveal his my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries not to the wiſe of this world, but to the ſimple and ignorant, as the face of the Primitive Church witneſſeth, which had very few learned men: which very thing evinceth the condition of ſimple men in point of Religion, to be if not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yet at leaſt equal to that of the learned. I am ſorry to dwell longer on a thing ſo evident. For theſe things cannot be obſcure to any one, but him, who being puffed up with a vain confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of himſelf, and his knowledge, hath quite evaporated and breathed-out all charity and mildneſs of Chriſtian forbearance. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch as erre are oftentimes by us accuſed of wickedneſs, not that they themſelvs erre grievouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but becauſe they think us to erre grievouſly. Our pride may ſeek what pretences ſhe pleaſeth, yet doth ſhe for the moſt part plead her own cauſe: &amp; a great part of thoſe that erre are dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; anathematized not ſo much for their own ignorance, as for their diſſent from us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:115483:24"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>That there is not in this life a perfect know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, and of Divine Myſteries, but in the other life; and that Faith, Hope, and Charity, are ſufficient to Salvation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF in the buſineſs of our Salvation a difference were made between the very work of our feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, and ſuch means as tend thereunto, we ſhould eſteem fewer things as neceſſary to be known, and a far eaſier courſe might be taken to repair con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in the Church. Whereas now, whilſt we confound the means with the end, it cometh to paſs that in a prepoſterous order we will have that which was firſt in the intention, to be alſo firſt in the execution, when notwithſtanding the means do in their nature ſo follow the end, as to go before it in time. What is it to which the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the nobleſt mindes aſpireth? Even the pleaſure of Eternal Joy, which mans minde can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo much as conceive, without the exact knowledge of God. But that contemplation, happy even to envie, awaiteth us in the heavens: nor can the narrowneſs of our earthly temper in this frailty comprehend it. As therefore he would be ridiculous, who ſhould hope for the fruit of ſoverain happineſs in this life: ſo are we alſo ſeiſed with a very fooliſh humour, whilſt in this Inne of our mortality we require of all the ſuiters for heaven, a perfit knowledge of Gods nature: which is not a taſte or hanſel of our fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115483:24"/>
but the very top and complement thereof. If the capacity of our underſtanding doth (as hath been ſaid) in vain attempt to comprehend this fully on the earth, it is fit that we, together with the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. knowing and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſying in part, expect the perfection that is to come. But with what ſpaces ſhall we circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe that wandering and imperfit knowledge? It is the ſafeſt way to ſet thoſe limits thereunto, which the very nature of the New Covenant hath appointed. Namely, that we chiefly and neceſſarily inculcate on all onely that knowledge of God and Chriſt, without which thoſe things cannot conſiſt, which are required of us by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the New Covenant. Of which ſort are a firm confidence placed in God and his Chriſt, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with a hope of his promiſes, and perfit charity. All theſe things are eaſily conſiſtent with thoſe miſtakes about the ſubtil ſearch into the nature of God and Chriſt. Moreover, the greateſt difficulty in ſuch diſſentions is for the moſt part wont to ariſe about the ſtate of our Saviour, before he repaired the lapſed condition of men. Howbeit, if we make a true eſtimate of the matter, although this myſtery of his Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity be true and altogether Divine, yet doth it not properly belong to us, to whom he hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented and revealed himſelf a Mediator in a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature and condition onely. So that they are altogether worthy of excuſe, who ſee and look upon him onely in that part, wherein he ſhewed himſelf to mankinde. For as they loſe not the rewards of a Covenant, who do not exactly know and comprehend his nature, with whom, and by the entermiſe of whom, they enter into
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115483:25"/>
league, ſo that they know both ſo far forth, as the reaſon of the Covenant, and common utility requireth: ſo neither ſeem they excluſible from heaven, who in the knowledge of God and Chriſt the Mediator want nothing to the reaſon and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of the New Covenant, although they riſe not up to the ſublimer contemplation of both. Eſpecially ſince the greateſt part of them, who at this day recede from the common ſenſe of the Church in ſo great a matter, are not out of any raſhneſs ſo perſwaded touching the Son of God, but rather out of a pious fear, leſt they ſhould detract from the Father ſomewhat of his honor. Wherein if they unwittingly offend againſt the Son out of love to the Father, (ſo that improbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty mingle not it ſelf with their error) it ſeemeth very credible, that the Son will, for the very love of the Father, forgive them this error. For he gave a notable proof of his meekneſs, when he prayed for his ignorant murtherers, as we alſo did before hint. What, think we, will not he do for the love of the Father, who for the love of Men forgave ſo great an injury to his enemies? Now if he out of love to mankinde doubted not to aſſume the form of a ſervant, and really to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure extreme diſgraces, certainly he will bear with the errors of men, who do not conceive wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily enough of his Majeſtie and Dignity, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that which is paſt. Will he, who for the ſakes of men did of his own accord debaſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the loweſt condition, puniſh them for this very thing, namely, becauſe they out of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance think more meanly of his condition, then is fit? Eſpecially when he himſelf by his debaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment did in a maner give an accaſion of ſuch ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115483:25"/>
Certainly it is incredible, that he who of his own accord underwent for the ſins of men a reproachful kinde of death, will not pardon to humane weakneſs a ſimple opinion, that dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates ſomething from his ancient Excellencie, if ſo be the error be harmleſs, and removed from all ſin of malice. More might be ſaid on this occaſion; but neither is it my intention to ſay all things, and what hath been ſpoken will ſuffice courteous judgements. As for moody diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, we may ſooner wiſh, then hope to bring them from their inbred prejudices. Now let us deſcend to ſuch things as are more ſpecial.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>A General Apologie for the</hi> Socinians, <hi>that they are not of ſuch a Perſwaſion out of Ambition, Avarice, Pleaſure, or Superſtition, nor offend out of any Malice, but onely out of the Care of their Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AY me! what contumacie is this, and ſcorning to obey, that we men depart from our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly allegiance in nothing ſooner, then that which hath moſt accurately been enjoyned and preſcribed? Doth that unhappie exile of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſolliciting the earth to a ſociety of rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, tempt us in that part chiefly, where he may make us moſt guilty of Treaſon? Or rather, did the Divine Providence more ſtrictly command
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115483:26"/>
that, wherein he moſt ſuſpected our obedience? Whatſoever it be, certainly the more frequently mutual love and good-will is enjoyned us in the ſacred Oracles, the more obſtinately do we refuſe it. And (which is the more to be lamented) we follow them as guides herein, who ought at no hand to go before us, I mean the Miniſters and Teachers of Religion, who being cozened with the zeal of inhumane piety, make it a part of our duty to hate diſſenters. A great part of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth to hate the perſons before the vices, and (which is a thing very unjuſt) under a pretence of the publike cauſe they exerciſe private hatred. Yea further, to an inexpiable and moſt hateful War, the bare name of parties is ſufficient: and in a prepoſterous order the judgement here fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth hatred and enmity, as elſewhere it doth love. Beſides, it is prejudicial to the truth to have been uttered or defended by ſuch as erre; nor is vertue valued at her worth in them, who have been once blaſted with the ſuſpicion and prejudice of errors. No honeſty, guilty of the leaſt hereſie, is ſafe in the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> nor is the honeſty of a Catholike more gently dealt withal amongſt Proteſtants, who being them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves alſo divided into ſundry factions, with proud determinations denounce heaven or hell to one another. There is no remembrance of mortality; no pardon to miſtaking, anywhere. Although you offend not in your maners, yet is it a capital offence to trip in the underſtanding of Divine matters. Yet hath the publike hatred of the world more eaſily conſpired againſt no ſort of men, then againſt thoſe who commonly paſs under the name of <hi>Socinians</hi> or <hi>Photinians.</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115483:26"/>
an unhappie race of men, and amidſt ſo many injuries and reproaches, honeſt in a maner <hi>gratis.</hi> For neither do I excuſe the errors which they hold. The thing I wonder at is this, How men ſo diſtant from all ambition and avarice, and innocent in all the parts of their life, ſhould be ſo grievouſly miſtaken. To aim at high matters, is the undoing of very many wits, born and fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the beſt things. But this vice, ariſing from the deſire of glory, hath there no place, (if other luſts be abſent) where ambition findeth not room enough for her ſwelling to expatiate in. For what man, being well in his wits, would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to himſelf a name of renown amongſt the moſt contemned and univerſally-hated part of the ignoble vulgar? Who would ſeek after the rays of an illuſtrious fame amidſt the darkneſs of obſcurity, who might finde it in the light and ſun-ſhine? As we ſee very many of them might do, whom neither the ſplendor of their birth, nor their wit and learning exempteth from a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary debaſement. Nor can you juſtly charge them with avarice, a great part of whom doth generouſly deſpiſe all means of growing rich; and you ſhall hardly finde anywhere either poorer men, or ſuch as by the rule of their ſect, are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated to give more then they. There re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth ſuperſtition, whoſe timorous nature al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways condemneth anothers liberty in that which ſhe her ſelf doth with a ſcrupulous religion refuſe. Certainly Superſtition is either baniſhed from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, or hath there put-off that which was in her nature moſt odious, ſince they in all their doctrines ſo diſſent from others, as that they exclude none either from eternal Salvation, or
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115483:27"/>
from brotherly communion, but ſuch a one as is a patron of manifeſt vice. Which very carriage wipeth away even the leaſt ſuſpicion of pride, which never debaſeth her ſelf unto ſo great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, as not to preſcribe that truth, which ſhe arrogateth to her ſelf, to be held and obſerved by all others almoſt under a form: ſo that I am utterly unable to finde out the cauſe, why they ſhould expoſe themſelves to the cruel hatred of all, and to dangers, unleſs it be an ardent deſire to pleaſe God, and ſtudy of true piety. In which regard they are worthy of more pardon, if any diſaſter befall them in the ſearch of ſublime things. For indeed I cannot apprehend what it is that inflameth us with ſo implacable preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice againſt them, when neither the ſweetneſs of fame, nor the ſpur of riches, nor the allurements of a diſſolute life, but onely the ſollicitous care of their ſalvation, hath caſt them into theſe ſtraits. We ought rather to favour the wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and reach forth a ſaving right hand to them, even againſt their will. Whereas now on the contrary we reject them ſuing for our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and had rather hate &amp; abominate, then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them in a friendly maner. But by what right, or for what demerit of theirs? Is it becauſe they defend things. which they conceive to be true, with ſo great prejudice to their honour and ſecurity? What? would we have them ſacrifice their faith and conſcience on the pleaſure of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? Or is it becauſe they think thoſe things to be true, which are falſe? Truly we are very injurious to mortality, if we ſuppoſe the errors and failings of our minde to be crimes. You will ſay, They ſin of ſet purpoſe: and fall not
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115483:27"/>
caſually, but by a voluntary ſlip. But who told you ſo? Or who hath diſcovered unto you their intimate counſels? Certainly not charity, which is an enemy to evil ſurmiſes, but bitterneſs and malignity of ſpirit, which is apt to make a ſiniſter conſtruction of anothers meaning. Although they had no evident proof of their innocency, yet in a doubtful matter, and ſuch as is known onely to the judge of hearts, it became us not to make any ſad decree againſt them. How much leſs can they be condemned, when there appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nothing that might invite and drive them to ſo wretched and dangerous malice? we ſhould at leaſt here make uſe of that notable ſaying of <hi>Piſo's, For what advantage is this done?</hi> For if they be neither ſeiſed with a longing after honours and riches, nor with an itch of pleaſures, nor can have any hopes of earthly ſolace; and if they conform their life to the preſcript of that moſt holy Law, where lyeth the incitement to ſo great improbity, as that they ſhould purpoſely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure to themſelves ſo many troubles together with eternal deſtruction?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:115483:28"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>An Anſwer to the Objection about reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the Conſent of the Church, for the Authority of the Scripture onely.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUt you will ſay, that they have been ſo daring as to queſtion a Myſtery for ſo many ages ſince received by all the Chriſtian world with great applauſe, &amp; venerable for its very antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ratified by the authority of ſo many Holy Fathers and Councels: and ſo are come to the very height of wickedneſs, in attempting to diſcuſs with ſacrilegious curioſity ſuch things as ought to be believed. The reprehenſion then is this, that they have begun to make a doubt of ſo certain a thing. But what? Is it unlawful to buſie your wit about a thing of undoubted truth, that after a more ſtrict examination you may the ſooner im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrate aſſent from your ſelf? Certainly it is a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement to the Truth, if we ſuppoſe her to be afraid of mens judgments. For neither is it unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming her to plead for herſelf at the bar of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that ſhe may bravely overcome, and draw the very judge to her ſide: whereas if ſhe decline the tryal of this court, ſhe ſuffers not a little in the confidence of her cauſe. For though we may not enquire into the truth of the Divine Oracle, yet we both may and ought into the true meaning thereof: and they are ſlanderers, who ſay that the <hi>Socinians</hi> believe not the words of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, becauſe they doubt of the received ſenſe. But what if they ſeem alſo to have juſt cauſes of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115483:28"/>
doubting? For they conceive that the Holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and the conſent of ſo many ages, do adde more dignity and veneration, then ſtreſs to the doctrine of the Trinity. How well grounded this conceit is, I diſpute not. However, certain it is, that they are not the firſt who have charged the publike authority of the Church, and the conſent of many Synods and ages, with the ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion of moſt grievous crimes. For ſince they ſee the foreſaid authority in many other things of great moment, not onely accuſed, but alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed of falſhood<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what ſo hainous crime have they committed, who dare not entruſt their faith and opinion of Divine things unto her? For of ſixteen ages, the twelve latter cannot warrant many things to the greateſt part of Chriſtians. It cannot be denyed that the <hi>Socinians</hi> going far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then others, do alſo reject the conſent of the four former, but eſpecially of the third and fourth ages. For ſince the Truth hath found little aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance in humane authority for ſo many ages of the loweſt antiquity, they thought that their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions were to be ſquared onely by the rule of the holy Scripture. Wherein truly they could not erre ſo greatly, but that they had a far greater cauſe of erring. For what could the faith of the Church, being once ſuſpected, ratifie to them? how could they know, that the Chriſtian world hath groaned under the darkneſs of errors no longer then for ten or twelve ages? Or that thoſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient times had any priviledge above the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ones, ſo that they could not erre? They ſaw them to be men, yea ſuch men as were, alas! defiled for a great part with vices and crimes. Nor could they be ignorant of the factions amongſt the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:115483:29"/>
Fathers, nor of their evident ambition, nor of the evil arts of ſundry others, nor of the ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful errors of men otherwiſe moſt holy. And though it were to be held that about the three hundredth yeer of Salvation the Church did ſtill retain the primitive Truth, yet in ſo many diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſo many adverſe Councels, they judged that at leaſt the choyce of the truer opinion did pertain to themſelves. In chuſing which, they ought not to follow the judgement of the ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Church, which had been already juſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in many points of fait<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but the infallible rule of the holy Scripture. For how could the Church warrant unto them the opinion of others, when ſhe was not able to make good her own. Beſides, they called to minde the <hi>genius</hi> of that age, and the diſpoſitions of thoſe Fathers, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning whom that great man <hi>Justus Lipſius</hi> in our age wrote, <hi>that many did then ſo put-on Christ by an outward profeſſion, that in their minde they did not put-off Plato.</hi> And therefore they not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe ſuſpected, that in many heads of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, plain words were wreſted to forrain and Philoſphical ſenſes, whilſt the Fathers did with ingenious comments tack the myſteries of their Philoſophy to the word of God, that they might not ſeem to have learned in vain. For what ſhould be the cauſe, ſay they, that touching the received explication of the holy Trinity, <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Triſmegiſtus</hi> ſpeak more clearly, then the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture? Or what reaſon ſhould there be, why the Scripture ſhould more timorouſly and obſcurely deliver ſo holy a Myſtery, then the foreſaid Philoſophers? Theſe and the like things,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115483:29"/>
though they do not acquit them of error, yet do they clear them from the imputation of raſhneſs. For nothing is more certain, then that the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt is not built on ſo weak a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, as ſome conſtitute in humane authority. Now did we heretofore wreſt theſe arms out of the hands of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> that we our ſelves might uſe them againſt others? Certainly it becometh not us either to take their weapons, or deliver ours up to them: but when we are ſummoned to the tribunal of the holy Scripture onely, we ought not to yield this p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aiſe to the Adverſaries, that they ſhould ſeem to hope better then we concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the equity and favour of ſo great a judge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>An Anſwer to three other Objections: a Compariſon of</hi> Calvin<hi>'s Doctrine touching Fatal Predeſtination, with the Doctrine of others.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUt it will be further objected, that the <hi>Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> impiouſly contradict the manifeſt words of the ſacred Scripture, and ſcornfully reject the clear Truth coming-in upon them. To which I anſwer, That whatſoever pains and travel they undertake in this buſineſs, is employed not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the holy Trinity, (as they are unjuſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famed) nor againſt the Sacred Scripture, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Humane Explications of both. Hence we may ſee that they willingly aſſent and give credit to all the Sacred Oracles touching this
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:115483:30"/>
matter, onely rejecting certain interpretations and forms, ſprung-up certain ages after. They believe that they are according to the command of Chriſt <hi>to be baptized into the Name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of the Son, and of the Holy Spirit,</hi> Matth. 28. They believe <hi>thoſe three ſacred Witneſſes in heaven, the Father, the Word, and the Holy Spirit,</hi> 1 Joh. 5. They acknowledge <hi>that in the beginning was the Word, and the Word was a God,</hi> Joh. 1. yet ſuch a one, <hi>to whom all power in heaven and earth was given,</hi> as he ſpeaketh of himſelf, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. It would be tedious to recko<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> up all the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture-teſtimonics of this kinde, to which they give credence without any exception. Thoſe hard and ſubtil opinions concerning the Eſſence and Perſon of God, concerning the communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of properties, and others of that batch, they either underſtand not, or think them repugnant to the ſimple and plain word of God. Give us leave, ſay they, to be ignorant of ſuch things as are believed with danger. In theſe ſo ſubtil and thorny explications, if they after the maner of men chance to erre, ſhall they preſently be ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the enemies of God and Chriſt? Shall there be found no pardon for an error in ſo great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of things; no excuſe for weakneſs? which notwithſtanding we ingeniouſly ſeek even for the greateſt crimes, though we be never ſo well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided of means to avoid them. Are they, who out of ignorance and error violate the Edicts of Princes, acquitted from the crime of treaſon? and ſhall he that offendeth about the Divine Oracles, in our opinion, have no refuge for his weakneſs in the mercy of the Heavenly Father? But you will reply, that their Blaſphemies are horrid,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:115483:30"/>
wherein impiety leaveth no place for pity; and reproachful againſt the Son of God, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing the foundation of our faith. To which I anſwer, that if there have been any amongſt them of a more intemperate tongue or quill, they are infamous not onely with us, but alſo with them. But what is here meant by the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Faith, I do not ſufficiently perceive. It hath been abundantly evidenced before, that ſuch errors do neceſſarily take away neither our Faith nor our Salvation. For it is not the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Salvation, to know his Eſſence, who hath promiſed the ſalvation to us, ſo that we have no impious and contumelious opinion of him: as the ignorance of the nature of the promiſer taketh not away the certainty of the promiſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he hath promiſed us anything under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of ſuch knowledge. As for the knowlege of the Father, they therein do in a maner agree with us. They likewiſe adore and reverence with Divine worſhip the Son of God, as the author and mediator of their Salvation, the heir and Lord of the Univerſe, and the General of our warfare. But you will here reply, that they deny his eternity. I anſwer, that they together with holy <hi>Paul</hi> care not much to know any thing, but Jeſus Chriſt, and him crucified; and had rather with ſo great an Apoſtle reſt in the ſimplicity of this knowledge, then either with <hi>Arius</hi> to aſcend to <hi>non-enliti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> or with <hi>Athanaſius</hi> to <hi>co-eſſentialities.</hi> As for the honour which they give to the Holy Spirit, the greatneſs thereof appeareth, in that they ſcarce diſtinguiſh him from the Supreme Father. Shall they then be ſaid to blaſpheme againſt theſe, if they be ſomewhat miſtaken in the other know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115483:31"/>
of them? Indeed many opinions are drawn out of their doctrines, that the wretches may be loaded with more envie, and that by them, who whilſt they are ſo vigilant in other mens errors, are faſt aſleep in their own. But if all the chaff were to be ſifted out of humane opinions, I would wiſh that a great part of the Reformed Churches would labour to defend their own cauſe, before they undertake to oppoſe that of others: but thoſe above all, who have from the age of <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſippus</hi> recalled down to theſe very times that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret and inevitable law of Fate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and who hold alſo, that the ſins and deſtruction of mankinde, and finally all and ſingular motions and impul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of our will, proceed from the Decree of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Deſtiny; to whom this falſe perſwaſion alſo ſeemeth to be fatal. From which opinion, if we lay aſide prejudice, more and more ſhameful errors will be deduced, then out of the books of <hi>Socinians.</hi> For which is more reproachful unto God, to hold that he is one as well in Perſon, as Eſſence; or (that I may clothe naked injuſtice with ſoft words) to bring-him-in puniſhing men, for not doing thoſe things, which by his own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement were impoſſible? Is it more abſurd to conceive that there is one Eſſence of the Father, another of the Son, then that God (I ſhudder to ſpeak it) hath one thing open in his tongue, and another thing, contrary thereunto, ſhut-up in his breaſt? This is reproach enough to the moſt high God, although we do not adde, that this diſſimulation is joyned with deceit? Is the dignity of the Holy Spirit more traduced, whilſt he is ſaid to be onely the vertue and power of God; then the goodneſs of God, whilſt he is
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:115483:31"/>
held the author of ſin? which conſequence doth alſo flow by a fatal and inevitable flux from that doctrine of Fate. For he that decreed men ſhould neceſſarily ſin, certainly would have them ſin: otherwiſe he would have decreed every thing againſt his owne deſire. Now he, whoſe decree and will the event doth immutably follow, may certainly be termed the cauſe of that event, whether he effect it by himſelf, or by another. Finally, is it a greater derogation to the dignity of Chriſt, to deny two natures in him, leſt we ſhould make him two perſons, then to the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, to affirm that he would perſwade men to that, whereto nevertheleſs he hath not perſwaded them, namely that he would give ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation unto all, when notwithſtanding he hath deſigned it onely to a few? Truly if we look more narrowly into the matter, the doctrine of the <hi>Socinians</hi> touching the Holy Trinity, is not to be accounted ſo much evil and impious in its owne nature, as imperfect, and maimed. For it ſeemeth to aſcribe to the Holy Trinity nothing falſe or abſurd, but only to take away ſomething that is true, namely the divine nature of Chriſt, and the proper perſon of the Holy Spirit. Whereas this doctrine touching the fatal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination of particular men, laboureth not with any defect, but with manifeſt ptavity. For it not onely offereth injury to God by moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy calumnies, but alſo ſtriketh at the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of our faith. For to omit ſecurity and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair, with which two rams it battereth the wall of our piety, it wonderfully weakneth the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry belief of Gods promiſes, whileſt it bringeth-in God wickedly diſſembling, the more is the grief!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:115483:32"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>Reaſons and Examples for tolerating Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks; and who are true Hereticks.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO what purpoſe ſpeak I theſe things? name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſhew that there is no cauſe, why we ſhould not think that they ought to be tolerated in the Church, whoſe tenets either by themſelves, or for their abſurd conſequences, ſeem ſcarce tolerable, ſo that they do not wilfully aſcribe ſome impious thing to God, and teſtifie their love towards the Lord Jeſus Chriſt by obeying his commandments. For although both the patrons of the forecited opinions did build unprofitable yea damnable tenets, as it were hay and ſtubble, upon our foundation, which is Jeſus Chriſt, yet, as it hath been alſo ſhewn at the beginning, the tenets, which they through error have brought in, ſhall be deſtroyed by fire, whileſt they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the mean time (unleſs ſome other thing hinder) ſhall, as the Apoſtle teſtifieth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. obtain pardon and ſalvation. Neither indeed ought we to refuſe or ſcorn their communion, whom God will receive into the ſociety of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal happineſs; nor ſhould we hate them on earth, to whom eternal love in heaven is due. We are unworthy to bear the title of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, if we diſdain to be their brethren, whoſe Father God deſireth to be. But if we be afraid of the contagion of ſuch errors either in behalf of our ſelves, or rather of the weaker ones, in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:115483:32"/>
the firſt place we may not thereupon renounce brotherly love, which we owe to them although they erre. For we ought not to forſake a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and clear duty, leſt an uncertain evil ſhould happen, nor to purſue even the moſt holy ends by unlawful means. But ſecondly, that fear is vain. For if we have not the truth, there is lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle danger to be feared from them, much leſs if we have it. For ſince they maintain their tenets with no arms, nor with any force, and think it not ſo much as lawful ſo to do, nor ſet them off with any carnal allurements, certainly the truth can never be by them either oppreſſed with force, or overthrown with fraud, inaſmuch as the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of truth is ſuch, that like to Eagles fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhe devoureth all other light plumage of opinions, never withdrawing her ſelf from us, unleſs ſhe be tyred either with our ſervitude, or ſins. Which twain being not to be feared by us in a modeſt liberty of diſſenting, and ſtudy of true charity, what cauſe is there why we ſhould ſo warily ſence our opinions from their tenets? Let us rather be poſſeſſed with a certain hope, that as earthen veſſels being joyned with thoſe of tin or ſilver, are broken to pieces: ſo alſo if God the author of peace ſhall bring bring back into the Church that happy tolerance, all falſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions fighting hand to hand with the the true, will be daſhed to ſhivers, and periſh. Otherwiſe if we ſo much fear that mutual patience, and friendly conference, we do not think well enough concerning the goodneſs of our cauſe. Hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when the dawning of Goſpel-light was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, <hi>Luther</hi> and his followers would have wiſhed that they might be tolerated in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:115483:33"/>
of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. But it concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Pope to ſecure his darkneſs, from the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the morning. Again, when a diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was riſen up between the <hi>Lutherans</hi> and the Reformed, who was it that refuſed the form of agreement that was offered, but he that doubted of his cauſe? Now alſo in the very reformed Church it ſelf, upon the diſſention concerning Fate, none are more diſpleaſed with tolerance, then they that ſuſpect the truth of their doctrine. Would error were ſo circumſpect in the cradle of its infancie, as it is provident being once grown-up. But it being blinde when it is born, doth afterward become ſharp ſighted, foreſeeing its fate afar off, and eſchewing it, and is never more ingenious to prolong its life, then when it is preſſed with the conſcience of its owne weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. But you will ſay, Shall we acknowledge a Heretick even for a brother, when the Apoſtle, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3. commandeth us to avoid him after two or three admonitions? why ſhall we be more merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful then the Holy Spirit? Let not that mercy turn to our miſery, when once the Lord begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to require at our hands the ſouls of ſo many ſeduced innocents. Shall we not eſteem him a Heretick who in ſo great a matter departeth from the ſound doctrine of the Church? do we not think our owne doctrine ſound? How often have they been admoniſhed both with writings and diſputations, and yet nevertheleſs ſtick to their errors as to rocks? I anſwer, Let none pleaſe himſelf ſo much, as to vie with the Apoſtolical meekneſs. It is an incurable member, that the Apoſtle enjoyneth to be cut off from the reſt of the Churches body. Howbeit there may be error
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:115483:33"/>
in them that undertake the cure, and they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves may be overſpread with much darkneſs. For neither can the ſound part be always diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from the diſeaſed one, and the one doth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes deceive us with the diſguiſe and image of the other: And though it be never ſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt what part is entangled with a true diſeaſe, yet doth it ſometimes remain to be ſcanned whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be to be cut off or cured with mollifying remedies; for thoſe members onely ought to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer amputation, wherein the gangrene leaves no place for a milder medicine. Nor is the Apoſtle of another minde, when he commandeth many admonitions to be premiſed before excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. And leſt it ſhould be doubtful whom he deſigned by the name of an Heretick, he ſubjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth arguments thereupon, which are indeed ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the Heretick himſelf, but unto us impul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive cauſes, that we may avoid him. For he ſaith, <hi>that ſuch a one is overturned, and ſinneth being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned of himſelf.</hi> And leſt any one ſhould think that theſe are indeed impulſive cauſes, but not of our fact, and our avoiding, but onely of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles injunction; ſo that he indeed for theſe cauſes excludeth every Heretick from the communion of the Church, but yet it is not neceſſary for us to have reſpect to them, he premiſeth the participle, <hi>knowing;</hi> to intimate that we alſo ought to know the cauſes, why we diſcommon any of the citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens in that heavenly commonwealth, nor haſten raſhly to ſuch Proſcriptions, but after we have certain knowledge of ſo great malice in them. And truely although the Apoſtle had not added this, yet did very charity, and the analogie of our Religion, dictate ſo much unto us. For this
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:115483:34"/>
is a great puniſhment, nor to be inflicted but on ſuch as ſin evidently. And foraſmuch as in ſo great a matter no error can be little, we ought firſt of all to be aſcertained, that the man to be condemned is worthy of ſo rigid a ſentence, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch a one, as is here painted out in his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours. Which not belonging unto men, who go aſtray from the common road, out of meer igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or injury of the times, what ſhall we do to them that make uſe of this exception? Shall they, who in theſe calamitous times, in this deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Church, (being born a great while after the riſe of Antichriſt, and not able fully to diſpel the darkneſs of that long night) turn aſide into by<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> paths, be judged to ſin out of perverſity of minde? Where now is that royal high-way, thorow which the godly may paſs ſecurely on with an unerring foot to Salvation? If it lie in the authority of the Church, ſhe hath now for many ages been beſet with the ſnares of Antichriſt. We wonder that they are afraid of the ſuſpected faith of the Church, when they do the ſame after our example, and in ſo great danger to fear even all the things that are ſafe is a point of prudence. And we ſtill dare to upbraid them with raſhneſs in departing from the common doctrine, when they ſeem to do it out of a juſt and well-groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded fear. But if this way conſiſteth in the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the holy Scripture, they do not ſtray from it, whilſt they together with us honour thoſe Sacred books with due reverence. But you will ſay, that the right and orthodox ſenſe of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture is rather the onely path, that is able to bring us to the very citadel of Truth. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that this way was heretofore worn with the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:115483:34"/>
publike going of Chriſtians; but now, being firſt hidden with the ſpringing briars of Antichriſt, and therefore trodden by very few, and not as yet diſcovered by having all the brake cut down, and beſides called into doubt by ſo many inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening falſe paths, it hath not as yet recovered the name and nature of a Royal high-way, which it had for a long time loſt. And therefore the greater pardon is due unto ſuch as deviate from the ſame. For neither do they erre through de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate malice of heart, who do not always walk therein amidſt ſo many croſs-ways and turnings. Let any one reckon up to me all the ſects of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, and I will ſay he is a brave fellow if he omit none. In ſo great a concourſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, if they have not choſen the truer, who will ſay that this is rather done out of improbity, then out of ignorance? For by what argument, after ſo many errors have been introduced, ought the Truth to lie open to their view? By the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous conſent of the Church? O unanimous conſent amidſt ſix hundred different ſects! You will ſay, that in the doctrine contrary unto them the greateſt part are agreed. But this is nothing, ſince they have alſo agreed in very many errors. So that we muſt again ſeek out a priviledge for the doctrine of the Trinity, whereby it came to paſs that though men erred in other points, yet could they not miſtake in this. But if we ſuppoſe that they ought to examine all opinions by the rule of the Holy Scripture, and afterwards to chuſe the truer; they have done both, ſave that in the latter they have not followed that which indeed was, but onely that which they thought to be truer. Which certainly is an error, and no
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115483:35"/>
malice; nor can they be ſaid to ſin ſelf-condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in holding ſuch an opinion, for which they are ready to loſe their life and fortunes. For neither doth he condemn himſelf, at leaſt in his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, who in the midſt of cruel tortures hopeth for eternal life from God, as the reward of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending the truth. Wherefore ſince we are not certain, that they are perverſe, and ſelf-condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but well aſſured that they are not ſuch, even from the death which they willingly undergo for their Errors; and ſince ſuch Errors (as hath been before proved) do not ſubvert eternal ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, it ſeemeth that they ought not to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregated from the communion of the Church, if they will teſtifie their love towards the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, by obeying his commandments.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>What Hereticks are to be excommunicated, what not; and a fuller Apologie for thoſe who in our Age paſs for Hereticks.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BY this reckoning, will ſome ſay, How few He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks muſt be excommunicated? who will not invent plauſible pretences for his pravity? There is no doctrine ſo abſurd and peſtilent, which being palliated with that cloke of error, may not creep into the Church. To which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that there is no cauſe why we ſhould be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous, leſt we ſhould have no occaſion to uſe this rigid law of excommunication. Would the Church had even at this day no voluntary rebels
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:115483:35"/>
againſt the Divine Majeſty. But neither in the times of the Apoſtles were there men wanting, who ſubverted either our faith in God, or the hope of immortality, or the piety and love that is enjoyned us, and ſuch as did not by deductions and conſequences, but with open face, as they ſay, vent blaſphemies and impieties. Whoſe endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and impiety is not ſo obſcure, but that it is apparent that they were conſcious to themſelves of their pravity and fraud. As if any one ſhould deny the reſurrection of the dead, who ſeeth not that ſuch a man, after he hath viewed the clear and certain ſentence of the Holy Scripture, will be convicted in himſelf, although he may perhaps diſſemble it? There is the ſame reaſon in the patron of ſome manifeſt vice. All which being manifeſt, (for ſo are the works of the fleſh) and manifeſtly forbidden, ſuch a man hath no ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-hole in the ambiguity or obſcurity of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture, unleſs he disbelieve the ſame, and ſo overthrow all Religion. Whoſoever therefore bring into the Church ſuch doctrines, as do in their own nature ſubvert our Salvation and Faith, they are deſervedly commanded to depart together with the former, not onely leſt they ſhould hurt others, but alſo becauſe they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as hath been ſhewn, are of incorrigible malice and perverſity, and conſequently ſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned. For a Chirurgian doth not preſently fear or cut-off an infected part, becauſe it may with its contagion hurt the reſt of the body, but would firſt have that very part cured of the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: which if it doth not ſucceed, he then cuts it off as incurable. But thoſe doctrines that ſtand not within the boundaries of neceſſity to ſalvation, are ſuch, that an errour in them, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:115483:36"/>
in this diſturbed ſtate of things, cannot be taxed of wilful pravity, nor can it either damn its author, or exclude him from the boſome of the Church. But ſome one will here object, Shall we brand with this ſpiritual cenſure the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate maintainer of none, even the greateſt er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, if ſo be it overthrow not our Salvation? But there are many things, which though in their own nature they take not from us our Salvation, yet do they by degrees ſo undermine and weaken the ſame, that afterwards it falleth down of its own accord. And do you like it, that ſuch diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſhould be cheriſhed in the Church? To which I anſwer, that I would have theſe diſtempers cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red without wounds and cauteries, eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Truth, unleſs it be oppreſſed by force, or ſcorned by men, who are blinde with the love of vices, is never wont to be ſupplanted by thoſe pernicious errors; yea this daughter and foſter-childe of time, always growing ſtronger with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry age, doth with the beams of her light diſſolve and melt all the waxen arguments of falſhood, unleſs one of thoſe twain before mentioned, doth hinder: both which ought to be baniſhed from the true Church of Chriſt. For ſince by force, or the allurement of our affections, as well falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood as truth may be promoted, (if yet truth may be ſo promoted) but by a free diſpute in mutual love, onely truth; and falſhood ſometimes put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on the vizo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Truth; it is a ſafer courſe to keep this way onely in the Church, which having ſhut-out error lyeth open to truth, then whilſt we endeavour by all means to inſinuate truth into men, to leave and prepare an entrance for falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. And therefore to caſhiere the lighter er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, (for the Objection ſpeaketh not of the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:115483:36"/>
lighteſt) the care and vigilancie of the Paſtors is ſufficient; who will finde that the love due to er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring perſons will no whit retard them in pulling up falſe opinions according to their ability. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, ſhould it never ſo much be granted, that in the infancie of the Church, and in her following growth, theſe errors, which outwardly appear ſomewhat light, but inwardly contain very much, were not tolerated, yet will it not be evinced from thence, that they ought not at this day to be tolerated in the old-age of the Church. For they deceive and are deceived, who model our times by the pattern of that flouriſhing age. The crazie health of the Church cannot be reſtored with the ſame remedies. Many things ſtifle a diſeaſe in the birth, which when it is grown up do foment it. When the Church was found and luſty, in the prime flower of her age, and whilſt the colledge of the Apoſtles was yet living, even violent remedies were to be uſed towards her, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of her vigour. Whereas now being ſpent with diſeaſes and old age, and become feeble, ſhe doth in a maner ſink under the weight of her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing ſickneſs, and is never in more danger, then when ſhe falleth into the hands of cruel Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. Heretofore her former vigor did admit the opening of a vein, and taking away of blood: but now after her ſtrength hath been exhauſted with ſo many maladies, if there be any vital juyce remaining, it cannot be let out, but the very life and ſpirit will iſſue forth together. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve me, ye that talk of nothing but launcets and cauteries, will with your unſeaſonable Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick kill the Church, if ye let out that little blood which is remaining, in this nick of time when ſhe ſeemeth to be almoſt a dying. Whatſoever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:115483:37"/>
have been invented for the health and conſervation of the Church, as this is touching the puniſhment of Hereticks, ſhould then, as pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence teacheth, be omitted, when they bring more hurt and danger, then profit. For why deſire we that the people of God ſhould like a lump of mouldring ſtuff be further crumbled into infinite pieces? What end of Schiſms will there be, if a promiſcuous diſſent be ſufficient to make a rent? Why take we pleaſure to behold not the coat onely, as a Great man wrote, but the very body of Chriſt, whereof he is the head, to be cut and torn in pieces? But let the reſpect of profit take place: let us ſee whether it be lawful for us at this time to chaſe thoſe erring perſons from the communion of Chriſts Church. For there is a wide difference between them, and thoſe hereticks that were contemporary with the Apoſtles. For ſuppoſe them, who now-a-days erre in matters of faith, to make their appearance before the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend conſiſtory of the Apoſtles and their aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates; ſuppoſe them to be often convicted and admoniſhed, and nevertheleſs to perſiſt obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, though in the leaſt error, who would not deteſt their malice? Certainly a very ſlight er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror would now be tranſmuted into the nature of a wicked crime. And why ſo? Becauſe they durſt reſiſt the holy Spirit ſpeaking by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles: and when they had no cauſe to queſtion the doctrine and faith of that moſt ſacred Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, unleſs they would withal queſtion the whole Chriſtian Religion, yet did not give credence thereunto, nor obey it, and nevertheleſs would be accounted Chriſtians. What madneſs, what wickedneſs, what perverſneſs was it, when by this very incredulity they do ſufficiently teſtifie that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:115483:37"/>
they were not Chriſtians, as who denyed belief to the Apoſtles and their aſſociates, and yet under a pretence of Chriſtianity, did peſter the Church with deceit and lyes? Beſides, the malice of ſuch men was in the beginning far more manifeſt, in that a blemiſh may ſooner be diſcovered in a clean body, then in one that is ſpotted. And therefore it was an eaſie matter to eſpie and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the wickedneſs of ſuch men, as did turn aſide out of the common road, that never had been called in queſtion. But now though we have a very ſtrong perſwaſion concerning the certainty of our faith, yet who hath herein given us cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or ſecurity, that we cannot erre? What Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel can we at this day imagine ſo uncorrupt, as that of the Apoſtles, or the Primitive Church? And yet how many Proſcriptions may you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold in this age? how many Decrees, whereby men for the ſlighteſt matters exclude one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of heaven and the Church? I ſpeak not theſe things, as if I thought any queſtion were to be made concerning the ſoundneſs of the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Opinion: but to make it plain, firſt, that we ought more timorouſly, then the Apoſtles here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, to condemn ſuch as are tardy in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half; and ſecondly, that we ſhould not in ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter matters be over-confident of our knowledge and perſwaſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and finally, that even in weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyer things, provided they do not ſubvert our faith in the Lord Jeſus, and the obedience of his commandments, we may and are bound to tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the weakneſs of ſuch as erre. For what mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters it, for me certainly to know that I hold the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving doctrine in theſe points, if this be not mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to all Chriſtians, or if I cannot always very clearly demonſtrate the fame to him that erreth?
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:115483:38"/>
Have not all a far juſter cauſe of queſtioning the true opinion now-a-days, then heretofore in the time of the Apoſtles? And ſuitably a man may very eaſily ſlip in ſuch things through impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which heretofore could not be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the intervening of extreme impiety. Nor is there need of malice for continuance in error, where prejudice is ſufficient, and a ſuſpicion of error firmly imprinted in the minde againſt the patrons of the true opinion. Which certainly may eaſily ſeiſe even on an honeſt heart, eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe every ſect of Chriſtians inſtil into their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſans at the firſt a hatred and abhorrencie of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, &amp; from their very cradle ſow in their hearts their own tenets, which having once taken root, can hardly be pulled thence in their riper age. Now what cruelty is it, to caſt out of the boſome and lap of the Church, ſuch perſons as are ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of honeſty and truth, yea ſeek an agreement, onely for thoſe errors, which have been implant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in them without any fault of theirs, and do not overthrow ſalvation? But they are Hereticks, and to be avoided, as ſuch who are condemned of their own conſcience. Yea for the fore-alleadged cauſes they are not condemned of their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; And therefore neither now to be avoided, nor Hereticks. Or if we take no compaſſion on them, yet let us at leaſt take pity on the very truth which we defend, whoſe growth we envie, firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we drive others from a neerer prying into her; and next, becauſe we teach by our own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, that ſhe, if charged with falſe ſuſpicions, of right may and ought to be excluded by other Chriſtian Churches.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115483:38"/>
            <head>The Poſtſcript to the Reader.</head>
            <p>LEst the following papers, Chriſtian Reader, being left empty, ſhould beguile thy ſight, I have thought good in this place again to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeak thee with a word or two. By this time thou haſt perceived our minde and drift, which both the author of this Diſcourſe had before his eyes when he wrote it, and I alſo when I publiſhed the ſame for thy behoof and benefit. If thou hast but a grain of can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor in thy heart, and wilt paſs ſentence according to the preſcript of Truth, thou wilt judge and call this Writing not Heretical but Peaceable. But you will ſay, What peace, what agreement either can or ought a Christian man to have with Hereticks? Good Reader, we undertake not the patronage of Hereticks. But before you exclude others out of the verge of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Charity, and throw the thunderbolt of an Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema upon them, you ſhould well weigh and conſider, to whom the crime of Hereſie is justly to be imputed. In paſſing cenſure upon Hereticks, it was not ſo eaſie a matter to miſtake in that Golden age, wherein the Christian Church was founded by the Apoſtles, and governed by themſelves, as is in this Age of ours. For though in thoſe beginnings of the Chriſtian Church there did divers errors, yea and hereſies ſpring up, nevertheleſs, from that confuſion of diſſenting opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, there were not peculiar Churches, diſtinguiſhed by divers forms of Confeſſions and Ceremonies, as yet ſtarted up, but there was then one onely Christian Church, and ſhe truly Apoſtolical, and in all points of doctrine, which ſhe profeſſed, of a ſound belief. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:115483:39"/>
to contradict this Church, and her doctrine, was truly blaſphemous, truly heretical: and whomſoever either the Apostles themſelves, or alſo other Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Doctors of the Primitive Church declared Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, they might alſo deſervedly be accounted ſuch by all Christians, and there was no danger of error in that cenſure, no not among the more ignorant Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, as following the judgement of the very Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, by whom thoſe Divine Governours of the Church were guided, as appeared by moſt evident arguments. But at this day inaſmuch as there are, alas! ſo many and ſo various Churches of Chriſtians, which of all will be ſo bold as to aſcend with like confidence to that of the Apoſtles, to that ſacred Tribunal, from which ſhe may pronounce ſentence on the rest, as He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical? It is out of controverſie, that ſuch an autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity can agree to no more then one of them. For the true Church can be but one: and onely the true one is able to judge and condemn all the rest as Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal. Now foraſmuch as amongst all thoſe Churches, which will at this day be called Chriſtians, (I justly here except the vain arrogancie of the Roman Church) none dares undoubtedly to arrogate to it ſelf the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible certainty of the Apoſtolical Truth in all the heads of her Confeſſion, it may hence clearly enough appear, that the cenſure of Heretical Pravity doth ſo evidently agree to none of them, that we deſervedly ought alſo to acquieſce in her determination. I am not ignorant of what the greateſt part of our Divines are here wont to reply. That the Primitive Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Church, ſay they, is ceaſed, we do not deny: yet inaſmuch as we have the doctrine of that Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned in the monuments of the Evangeliſts and the Apoſtles, we cannot chuſe but pronounce them Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, who contradict the doctrine there expreſſed. I
<pb facs="tcp:115483:39"/>
alſo, dear Friends, eaſily permit, that in this diſpute of ours, the Divine Writings of the Apoſtles ſtand in this ſtead, ſo that he which contradicteth them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e no leſs eſteemed an heretick, then he that heretofore contumaciouſly oppoſed the Apoſtles preaching by word of mouth. But even thus can we not chalenge that cenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rian r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d againſt Hereticks. For they, whom ye place in the rank of Hereticks, are ſo far from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting the Holy Scripture, that they wage war a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you out of the ſame, and appeal to the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, not without a certain hope of victory, in the examination of their cauſe, inaſmuch as they embrace the Scripture in all things with as great ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of minde as you do: nor amongſt all the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Churches, which are at this day extant, ſhall ye ſhew any one, (that I know of) which doth not religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and from the heart yield an undoubted aſſent to all thoſe things, that are propoſed and taught in the Holy Scripture. Wherefore there is no cauſe why ye ſhould condemn any one of them for hereſie, ſince they agree with you in giving due credence to the Sacred Writ. And therefore whatſoever pretence ye ſeek for your carnal zeal againſt ſuch as you call Hereticks, yet to indifferent judgements can no other ground hereof appear, then their diſſent from your interpretation of the Holy Scripture, as to the controverted doctrines. But I will here bountifully grant you, that ye have in all things hit the true ſenſe of the Scripture, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it. Nevertheleſs it is further requiſite, that ye make this plain to them, whom ye brand with the crime of Hereſie. But what here is the ſtreſs of your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments? Ye appeal again to the Holy Scripture, and from thence condemn Hereticks. But they have already ſtricken this weapon out of your hands, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Holy Scripture maketh for y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, onely in
<pb facs="tcp:115483:40"/>
your own ſenſe and interpretation, and that they are accordingly condemned by you, not from the ſacred Scripture, but from your interpretation of the ſacred Scripture. And this is the circle of your arguing, which they deſervedly reject. Draw-out therefore againſt Hereticks thoſe truly Apoſtolical weapons, not the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>raſonical prating of the Chayr in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, but the power of the holy Spirit, wherewith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles being indued, could deliver Blaſphemers to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 20. and ſlay Hypocrites with the ſpeaking of a word, <hi>Act.</hi> 5. If ye want the powerful efficacie of this Spirit, acknowledge your raſhneſs and iniquity in condemning them, to whom ye are not able with evident and ſufficient arguments to demonſtrate your interpretation of the holy Scripture, and who by the ſame right, and from the ſame foundation object to you not onely errors, but alſo hereſies. Ye know that of Chriſt: <hi>Condemn not, and ye ſhall not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.</hi> What account will ye give to this juſt Judge, for ſo often violating this precept? Your zeal of the Divine Glory will not then excuſe you: for though it palliate it ſelf under this reverend name, yet is it wholly of the fleſh, and odious to God. But if ye affirm that it proceedeth from the Holy Spirit, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce arguments worthy of ſo great an Author. For neither i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this Spirit ſo weak, but that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e can ſhew forth tokens of his Divine authority and preſence in his Miniſters, and by them againſt his enemies. But whither am I carried away? I beſeech thee, good Reader, to pardon this digreſſion of mine; and having liked the pious counſel of our Author, intreat God, that he would inſtil into other Readers alſo a minde ſtudious of peace and concord. <hi>Farewel.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:115483:40"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Theſe books are to be ſold by</hi> Richard Moon, <hi>at the ſeven ſtars in</hi> Paul<hi>'s Church-yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A <hi>Pathway</hi> unto <hi>Englands</hi> perfect ſettlement, and its centre and foundation of Reſt and Peace diſcovered, by Capt. <hi>Robert Norwood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. <hi>An Additional Diſcourſe,</hi> relating to the Treatiſe aforeſaid. By Capt. <hi>Robert Norwood.</hi> Many things therein are fully opened, ſeveral Doubts and Objections anſwered; a brief ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count given of the Ancient Laws, Cuſtomes, and Conſtitutions of this Nation before and ſince the Conqueſt, ſo called.</p>
            <p>3. The Life of that incomparable man, <hi>Faustus Socinus Senenſis,</hi> deſcribed by a <hi>Polonian</hi> Knight. Whereunto is added, An excellent Diſcourſe which the ſame Author would have had premiſed to the Works of <hi>Socinus.</hi> Together with a Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of thoſe Works.</p>
            <p>4. <hi>Brevis Diſquiſitio:</hi> or, a brief Enquiry tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching a better way then is commonly made uſe of, to refute Papiſts, and reduce Proteſtants to certainty and unity in Religion.</p>
            <p>5. The Apoſtolical and true opinion concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Holy Trinity, revived and aſſerted; partly by 12 Arguments levied againſt the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional and falſe opinion about the Godhead of the Holy Spirit; partly, by a Confeſſion of faith touching the three Perſons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>John Biddle</hi> Mr. of Arts.</p>
            <p>6 A ſhort Treatiſe touching the death of Chriſt; alſo, the point of baptiſm is handled, with the
<pb facs="tcp:115483:41"/>
qualifications &amp; demerits ſufficient to the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in and caſting out Church-Members. By <hi>J. Dell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>7. The Army Vindicated in their late diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Parliament. By <hi>John Spittlehouſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>8. A Warning-piece diſcharged: or, certain in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence communicated to his Excellency the Lord Generall <hi>Cromwell.</hi> By <hi>John Spittlehouſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>9. The firſt Addreſſes to his Excellency the Lord General, with the new Repreſentative ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by him and his Councel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>John Spittle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>10. The new Earth, or, the <hi>Magna Charta</hi> of the paſt Ages, and of the Ages or World to come; called, The <hi>Jews</hi> Commonweal. By <hi>Joh. Brayne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>11. The unknown being of the Soul and Spirit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>John Brayne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>12. The Way of diſputing practiſed by Chriſt and his Apoſtles in deciding the Controverſies of that Age, and the Rule for the determining of our own: or, the right uſe of ſpiritual weapons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>John Brayne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>13. Baptiſm without Baſon: or, plain Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture Proof againſt Infant-Baptiſm, in Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> Arguments, and the Exercitations of Mr. <hi>Sidenham.</hi> By <hi>William Kaye,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>keſley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe things he hath now in the Preſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Judah's Witneſs ſounding the Trumpet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Cryer in the Wilderneſs of <hi>England,</hi> decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Baptiſm of the Eternal Spirit to be the onely Baptiſm in Chriſts Kingdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>Edward Punch.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:115483:41"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
